<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A testimony to the true Jesus and the faith of him wherein the way of the people called Quakers is in meekness and righteousness summed and weighed, first in a general examen of their spirit and chief principles, after in a particular review of the same as it is distinctly set forth in a book of theirs, called, Love to the Lost : wherein are many things useful for the discerning of spirits in this hour of darkness and temptation / by T. Higgenson.</title>
            <author>Higgenson, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 210 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43749</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1950</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31109</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11779509</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11779509</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48979</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43749)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48979)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1485:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A testimony to the true Jesus and the faith of him wherein the way of the people called Quakers is in meekness and righteousness summed and weighed, first in a general examen of their spirit and chief principles, after in a particular review of the same as it is distinctly set forth in a book of theirs, called, Love to the Lost : wherein are many things useful for the discerning of spirits in this hour of darkness and temptation / by T. Higgenson.</title>
                  <author>Higgenson, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 84, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Brewster ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes table of points discussed.</note>
                  <note>Numerous errors in paging.</note>
                  <note>Author summarizes points of James Naylor's "Love to the Lost", beginning on p. 47.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  England --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48979:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TESTIMONY TO THE TRUE JESUS And the Faith of him, Wherein the Way of the People called QUAKERS is in Meekneſs and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſummed and weighed.</p>
            <p>Firſt in a General Examen of their ſpirit and chief Principles; after in a particular reveiw of the ſame, as it is diſtinctly ſet forth in a book of theirs, called, <hi>Love to the Loſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein are many things uſeful for the diſcerning of Spirits in this hour of darkneſs and temptation.</p>
            <p>By T. HIGGENSON.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Brewſter</hi> at the three <hi>Bibles</hi> near the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:48979:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48979:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Teſtimony to the True JESUS, and the Faith of Him.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Oncerning the People called Quakers, and that way, a ſum of their faith &amp; profeſſion is come forth ſigned by <hi>James Naylor,</hi> who ſeems to be cheif; whereby having ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained through Grace a more perfect un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of them then I had before, his Trumpet giving a more certain ſound than others had done: and having obſerved that Spirit to ſhew it ſelf therein with more nakedneſs and leſs covering (at leaſt to me) than at other times; I ſhall in righteouſneſs and love to them and others preſent a veiw thereof according to the ſame form and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage it there preſents it ſelf under.</p>
            <p>The ground of my appearing herein is, not any intereſt I have in Court or Clergy, from both whom I ſtand at a diſtance ſo farre as they appear at a diſtance from Chriſt and his work; not any zeal I have to any form or way of worſhip cryed down by this people; my heart is knit to all the Lords people, from the Prieſt to the darkeſt forms, though I am not joyned to them outwardly in the letter; nor that I am ignorant or a ſtranger to ſpiritual myſteries or inward truths, at leaſt in part; touching which I may ſay, that my thoughts and zeal for Chriſt within have abounded ſo above the thoughts I had of his bloud without, that I account it infinite mercy. I am not at this day in unity with that Spirit that makes the death of Chriſt of none effect, inſtead of this my appearing againſt it: but my ground is this, that I might bear ſome teſtimony to the bleſſed Myſtery of Chriſt crucified, and againſt this or any people, ſo farre as they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear againſt it: and that according to my meaſure I might ſet forth
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:48979:3"/> and juſtifie the harmony that is between the perfect Redemption in Chriſt for <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and the Revelation of him in us: which two have been <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Myſtery of Iniquity divided and ſet up one againſt the other; the firſt againſt the laſt, by men zealous for the dead faith of Chriſt without, againſt his Spirit; and the laſt againſt the firſt, by men pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to the Myſtery of Chriſt in them, againſt the Redemption in Chriſt for them.</p>
            <p>The Law was given by <hi>Moſes</hi> in darkneſs, blackneſs, and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts, and with loud noiſes; but Grace and Truth came by Jeſus Chriſt, in a ſtill and meek way, no cry nor voyce to be heard in the ſtreets; like as it was then, ſo will it be now; if the loud noiſes of the Commandment and Condemnation by <hi>Moſes</hi> be brought in again, the ſtill voyce of Reconciliation and Peace by Chriſt may not be heard as to many.</p>
            <p>The Law was given by him that ſpake on Earth, commanding things to be done by men in the fleſh; the Goſpel by him that ſpake from Heaven revealing our Righteouſneſs already wrought in the Lord himſelf: as many as are not ignorant of Sathans devices doe know, how eaſily, having begun in the Spirit, we return back to the bondage of the firſt, but how hardly we ſtand faſt in the Loyalty of the ſecond: if ſuch a ſpirit or faith ſhall cover this Land, that ſaith, we are not perfected for ever in Chriſt the Head, before any good be done in us, what remaines then but that ſacrifices for ſin be offered again, though not in the Temple at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> yet in the Temples of our bodies, and ſo build up again the old worldly Sanctuary, onely changing the manner and form of adminiſtration.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the Righteouſneſs of the Letter, of Angels, and of God.</head>
               <p>VVHat may be uſeful for us to know, as to the general Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of this and many other Spirits, the things follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing may in part acquaint you, in whoſe hearts the faith and love of Truth does yet remain.</p>
               <p>There is a Righteouſneſs according to the Letter, conſiſting of bodily exerciſes in the earthly members after the outward Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, which is but the purifying of the fleſh, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 9.13. herein ſtood the Religion of the carnal Jews under the firſt Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; this became a covering upon their eyes, a vail upon their hearts, that they could not ſee nor receive him who was the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:48979:3"/>
               <p>There is a Righteouſneſs of Angels, or a worſhipping of Angels <hi>Col.</hi> 2. which is the Spirit of Man retired into things within, paſſing beyond the things of the letter, or of the body into ſpeculations of the Godhead, underſtanding of Myſteries, to a certain perfection of knowledge and holineſs, all which is but the Glory of Man: herein ſtands the Religion of the Anti-chriſtian Gentiles now under the new Teſtament: this was the ſum of all the divinity the School-Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors did know or deliver: this Angelical Perfection (falſly ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led) laid the foundation of the Eremites living by roots in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, of Anchorites ſhutting up themſelves from Communion with men, of Monaſteries and holy Houſes, for mortifying the fleſh, and perfecting in holineſs: theſe things, while they bear a ſhew of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in humility and neglecting the body, have been in every age, and ſtill are ſet at enmity againſt him, who is the Righteouſneſs of God, in the ſeveral approachings and manifeſtations of himſelf; ſo what Sathan cannot do in a weaker way by the Righteouſneſs of the letter, he will endeavour to effect by a Miniſtery of Light and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes; that appearing as in the glory and purity of an Angel of God, he may darken or diminiſh the righteouſneſs and glory of the Son of God.</p>
               <p>There is the Righteouſneſs of God, Jeſus Chriſt, who by that ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Spirit and Life dwelling in him, did at once, and for ever; not in ours, but his own body, triumph over, and put an end to the Law, Sin and Death on his Croſs, and riſing from the Grave, raiſed up, and ſet up, together with himſelf, his Church in the heavenly Righteouſneſs in him: this Righteouſneſs is as farre above either of the former, as Chriſt is exalted above all Principality and Power; therefore can they not add nor extend any righteouſneſs to this, no more than the Glory of Man or Angels can add glory <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>This Righteouſneſs is the Word made fleſh, not the W<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> alone, nor the fleſh alone, but the Union of theſe, God and the <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>n Chriſt in One, and the operation proceeding from this Union wrought and remaining in the Perſon of Jeſus Chriſt: this Righteouſneſs being broad and perfect, according to the Perſon in whom it is, extends it ſelf unto all and upon all that beleive, and <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> them perfect and without ſpot to God in it ſelf, without and before any work or good done whatſoever: let this righteouſneſs ſhine forth <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ongſt us, and our eyes ſhall be kept ſeeing, our judgement ſound <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> either philoſophy of men, nor perfection of Angell ſhall ſpoil us; neither
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:48979:4"/> iniquity in the Letter not in the Myſtery ſhall beguile us; but where this Righteouſneſs is denied or out of ſight, there darkneſs had co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered the mind, there ſpiritual wickedneſs will be taken for Goſpel-myſteries.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>What is Idolatry: God may be known three manner of wayes.</head>
               <p>AMong the works of the fleſh, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.20. Idolatry is one, the knowledge and worſhip of God according to the Law, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Philoſophy, and not after Chriſt, this is Idolatry; until Chriſt be formed in thee not as a Law-giver, but as a meer Saviour, not onely as putting away ſin and perfecting righteouſneſs in thee, but as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving already put it away, and perfected thee in himſelf, thou art in Idolatry, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 9 26. and 10.14. That of God which is manifeſt in all men, preſents God according to one form in his eternal Power and Godhead: <hi>Moſes</hi> preſents God in another form, in his back parts, as a Law-giver and a Judge: Chriſt preſents his face to us, Glory in the Higheſt, Peace on Earth, good will towards men; all theſe prepared already: Hence may be obſerved:</p>
               <p>That God may be Known three wayes: firſt, to that in every man by the things that are made: this may diſcover to men the inviſible things of him, his eternal Power and Glory, but not his good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure or purpoſe of Grace, this may raiſe up to high imaginations of the divinity, as over all, through all, and in all to a glorious ſhew and height of ſeeming holineſs and perfection, but knows nothing of the Myſtery hid in God, redemption by Chriſt, nor can lead any into it; unto theſe Chriſt crucified is fooliſhneſs.</p>
               <p n="2">2. God may be known by the Law from Mount <hi>Sinai;</hi> but this fight is ſo terrible, that <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid, <hi>I exceedingly fear and quake:</hi> this knowledge exerciſeth the body, purifies the fleſh, compels unto works, but opens not the way into the Holieſt, the heavenly righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs hid with Chriſt in God: unto theſe Chriſt crucified is a ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling block.</p>
               <p n="3">3. God is ſeen in the face of Jeſus Chriſt, without a vail, as in a glaſs; there is one God, and one Mediatour between God and men, the Man Chriſt Jeſus, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. the inviſible, inacceſſible God comes down in the Man Jeſus, and appears in him as upon a Mercy-ſeat, unto him let all men look that would ſee the Father: the cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of his fleſh was the renting of the vail, that Grace and Glory before hid in God might now ſhine forth in him: ſo Jeſus Chriſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:48979:4"/> alone in his Perſon is the face and Image of God, wherein he may and will be ſeen. If any man, though an Angel from Heaven, ſhall not point you unto a crucified and glorified Jeſus for fight and acceſs to God, know this, that he leads you out from the New and Living way, unto the old and deadly Gate, where the flaming Sword turns every way, that no fleſh can enter in and live, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.24. Curious ſpeculations of the divine Majeſty without Chriſt Jeſus, are the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per work of Reaſon, and the higheſt divinity of Philoſophers, Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites and Juſtitiaries; if thou thinkeſt to approach the divinity, h<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Light and holineſs, excluding the Mediator, thou ſhalt be confound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of his Glory. Let <hi>J. Naylor</hi> and his followers with fear and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling hear and conſider.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Who hold not the Head, and how Chriſt is Head.</head>
               <p>DOctrines and Spirits are ſpoken of fair in ſhew, high and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, which yet hold not the Head, <hi>Col.</hi> 2. what are the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, and what is the Head? the Doctrines are firſt of men; ſuch are they who come in the words and wiſdom of Man; their Doctrine a leaven of the Phariſees, that is a compound of humane wit and learning, Law and Goſpel letter, Jeſus Chriſt having onely a Name among them, himſelf being not beleived nor known by them, neither in his crucified body, nor quickening Spirit; theſe being of a lower and common nature are received by the greater part of men.</p>
               <p>Secondly, there is a doctrine of Devils, of Sathan transformed into Angels of light; ſuch preach a Jeſus, Goſpel and Spirit, but not the true; ſpeak great things, abſtaining from meats, from marriages, neglecting of the body, as things baſe &amp; ſenſual; imagine &amp; intrude into things in ſhew more excellent, things not ſeen, purity, perfection life of Angels; but the true perfection and life which is in Chriſt alone they deny, and ſet up another in work; that which is prepared and finiſhed already in one, the body of the Man Chriſt they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy, and teach another to be wrought or done again in many by Angel or Spirit, in the bodies of all the Saints; theſe are they who worſhip Angels, who hold not the Head; their doctrine by how much in ſhew more ſpiritual, by ſo much does it ſpoil and bewitch the minds of men above all other.</p>
               <p>What then is the Head?</p>
               <p>The Head over all things, the Head of the Church is Chriſt, of this
<pb facs="tcp:48979:5"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> underſtanding; Firſt according to his Godhead onely; that God is Head over all things, to be feared and worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped of all men; thus Jews, Turks, Pagans and all men do know and profeſs; this is that which may be known of God by all men, and is manifeſt in them, the enlightening upon every one that comes into the world. Secondly, according to the whole Perſon, God and Man in one; as ſuch he received power to become Head over all things to his Church; againſt him drove two great and dreadful enemies, the hand-writing of Ordinances, charging our ſins and Curſe upon him, and Principalities and Powers with their ſpiritual wickedneſſes to have ſwallowed him up; againſt both theſe he prevailed, blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out the one, having nailed it to his Croſs, and ſpoiled the other, making a ſhew of them openly, and triumphing over them in it: and thus he was declared Head over all things, which is to be rightly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, not onely as he is in the form of God, equal with God, able to ſubdue all things in us to himſelf (for this is true of him, had he never been manifeſt in fleſh at all, and is known and profeſſed by all Nations, though they beleive not, or know nothing of Chriſt come in the fleſh, as Jews and Pagan;) but he is Head according to his whole Perſon, <hi>Emmanuel,</hi> God and Man in Union; in that, not often and in every generation, and in many bodies, but in one body by one of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering once and for ever he hath, not in our Perſons, but in himſelf al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſubdued for us all things whatſoever are named in heaven, on earth, or in the deeps, the Law, ſin and death, with all their might, dominion and power. Hence are theſe ſayings faithful and true, and if any Man or Angel preach another Doctrine, beleive him not.</p>
               <p>That Jeſus Chriſt the brightneſs of the Fathers glory has already by himſelf without us, and before any good wrought in us, finiſhed tranſgreſſion, made an end of ſin, aboliſhed condemnation and death, and that not by Spirit onely, but by ſpirit, water and bloud.</p>
               <p>That though in the Kingdom of the Law, of Reaſon and ſenſe, that is, in the fleſh, ſin, condemnation and death are ſeen and felt; yet in the Kingdom of Grace and Faith, that is, in Chriſt, they are vanquiſhed and appear no more.</p>
               <p>That a beleiver while encloſed and ſhut up in a body of ſin and death, fightings and fears within and without, as he is in fleſh, is at the ſame time raiſed up into the heavenly righteouſneſs, immortality and freedom above all ſin or ſhadow of evil, as he is in Chriſt the Head;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:48979:5"/> as redeemed in Spirit, a Chriſtian is in heaven, in reſt, in victory and perfection; as not yet redeemed in the body, he is on earth, in la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, infirmities and imperfection.</p>
               <p>Theſe bleſſed ſayings, whoſoever holds faſt in faith and love, will be in him as a lamp leading him through the thick vail of Legality, the vain ſpeculations of Philoſophy, the myſterious depths of Anti-chriſt; and will be to him a Light to diſcern the Doctrine, Spirit, Miniſtry and Church of Chriſt, from them that ſay they are ſo, and ſeem to be ſo, but are not, but are of the Synagogue of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than.</p>
               <p>Ye are compleat in him. Upon this truth has the Church of Chriſt been built, as upon a rock, higher than all the flouds and ſtorms that have gathered againſt her during the long Night of Anti-chriſtian darkneſs; as this Truth ſhined forth, literal and myſtical Idolatry in <hi>England, France</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> as ſhadows of the Night fled away: On the other hand, this Truth dying and decreaſing out of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of <hi>Galatia, Coloſſe,</hi> &amp;c. prepared the way of the Man of Sin into them, and to this day hath exalted him over all Nations: when the knowledge of Chriſt as Head ſhall more encreaſe, and the Church grow up more into him who is Head, Anti-chriſt in his higheſt forms, his deepeſt ſpeech, his faireſt ſhews, worſhipped and wondered at by the unbeleiving and unſtable world of Profeſſors ſhall be revealed and conſumed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Three cheifeſt Principles of this people called <hi>Quakers,</hi> examined and weighed.</head>
               <p>COncerning this people, paſſing by their language poſtures, and all other reſpects as to Perſon or Circumſtance; the tryal and knowledge of theirs or any other Spirit may more certainly be had from the ſubſtance and ground of their doctrine and faith; the ſum and ſcope whereof (as to me it appears) may be fully and faithfully gathered up in theſe three following principles.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the Light which enlightens every man, accuſing of ſin, is Chriſt and God, the Pure and Perfect, the Eternal and Juſt One, and ſo the Redeemer and Saviour, and the All, to be known and beleived, not as do others, in word, letter, or perſon without, but as within, redeeming, reconciling and making attonement, not without in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but within in our ſelves; out of which Light man departing was loſt in darkneſs and the fall; into which Light returning again,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:48979:6"/> he is reſtored and redeemed as at the beginning.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That this Light as condemning of ſin and death, and reſtoring out of it into Righteouſneſs and Life, this is the bloud and death of the Croſs, the reſurrection and ſecond coming of the Son of God; and that Obedience without mixture unto this Light working all our works in us, this is our Redemption, Juſtification, Mortification and Sanctification; ſo much obedience, ſo much redeemed: thus the Law and Goſpel, Faith and Obedience, Death, Reſurrection, Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Juſtification and Sanctification are not things diſtinct, but one and the ſame within us.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That the way to come to all this, and to Chriſt, and the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is the Light in every man condemning of ſin, the ſure word of propheſie, wherein we muſt wait within, and not as others, go out unto a Chriſt without, a letter without; Chriſt and the Scriptures onely delivering their own experiences and conditions not as a Rule or word of faith to others; and giving their Teſtimony onely to the Light within, &amp; not to any Perſon, Redemption, or operation with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out; alſo his and their Miniſtration in work, words, or letter, without being onely the literal Covenant that makes nothing perfect. This is the juſteſt deſcription, and my trueſt underſtanding I can give of their faith and principles; their other doctrine are but concluſions proceeding from theſe.</p>
               <p>Three Principles of Truth are perverted and denied by theſe three principles of theirs; the Perſon of Chriſt as the Object of Faith: the Scriptures as the Rule of Faith, and Faith it ſelf as the evidence of things not ſeen: of each of theſe a word, whereby both Truth and Errour may appear.</p>
               <p>Jeſus Chriſt was in the beginning with God, the Word, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, the Life; yet fore ordained in the end of the world to be manifeſt in fleſh, to put away ſin therein by the ſacrifice of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
               <p>Unto him, that is, Chriſt as to come in the fleſh, the two great wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes under the old Teſtament, the Law and the Prophets did teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie and point as the true Promiſe and Sacrifice; the Law having a ſhadow of things ſeen afarre of, not then received; of good things to come, not preſent and done; of Jeſus the High-Prieſt to miniſter in fleſh, and therein to offer himſelf the one, the perfect, the eternal Sacrifice once and for ever, no more to be offered from thenceforth in any age or generation.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:48979:6"/>
               <p>In the fulneſs of time, the Word was made fleſh, and being greater than <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Prophets, or <hi>John,</hi> he gathered up their ſeveral mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations and finiſhed them in himſelf; the fulneſs of the Godhead in him, as a Sea of righteouſneſs, life and bleſſing, aboliſhing and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelming the ſin, condemnation and curſe of the world, as the leſs is overcome of the greater.</p>
               <p>And hereunto when he aſcended on high, he gave gifts unto men, whom he ordained as Apoſtles and Witneſſes to the world, that the Purpoſe and Grace which was given us in Chriſt before the world began, which was ſhadowed by the Law and foretold by the Prophets, was now made manifeſt by the appearing of our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, who hath aboliſhed ſin and death in his crucified body, and hath brought forth immortality and life in himſelf in ſpirit.</p>
               <p>Thus the Myſtery of Grace and truth lay hid in the divinity, but came forth, and was acted in the humanity; neither is the divinity without the humanity, nor the humanity without the divinity but both one in Chriſt: thus the crucified and glorified Perſon of Chriſt is the expreſs Image of God, the alone object of faith, the way whereby God came down in ſalvation unto men and by which we aſcend and have acceſs unto God: thus Redemption and Righteouſneſs is glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly wrought without us in the perſon of Chriſt; to point to any Perſon or Spirit within for the working Redemption over again, other than to him that deſcended and aſcended again, is to bring Chriſt down from above, and up again from the dead, to raiſe up <hi>Moſes</hi> out of his Sepulcher, which no man knows to this day, with his miniſtration of death, and to make the bloud of Chriſt a common thing, or as the bloud of another Man: conſider this and fear ye peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of whom I ſpeak.</p>
               <p>To conclude this firſt principle with one other note: the Perſon of Chriſt and Redemption in him is vailed and denied by two ſorts of men, legal Teachers of the Goſpel, and myſtical Teachers of the Law; they differ herein, the firſt ſet forth Chriſt in words of mans wiſdom, conditions of law, and as onely in the fleſh without, not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning him ſpiritually: the other ſpeak of him in more ſpiritual words and deep ſpeculations, but onely as redeeming within us, in ſpirit, not diſcerning nor beleiving the Glory of that Redemption without us in his Perſon; they agree in this, by both Chriſt is known onely after the fleſh, by the one onely as in the form of a Man or Perſon without, by the other as a Redeemer onely within, that is, as not having finiſhed already Redemption on earth, nor as being
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:48979:7"/> Head over all things in the Father: wherefore to know Chriſt as having aleady redeemed by his bloud without, and as the incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible fulneſs of Spirit, and life above all, through all, and within all his people, this is the true, the ſafe, the bleſſed knowledge of Chriſt; and by this the firſt of their Principles above named is weighed and reproved of errour.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How Faith is the evidence of things not ſeen.</head>
               <p>COncerning Faith; it is the evidence of things not ſeen: heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things were in God from everlaſting by way of purpoſe, yet unſeen, unſearchable by any eye; in fulneſs of time they were mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted in the Perſon of Chriſt, as by him perfected and wrought at once, yet ſeen and diſcerned onely by faith; according to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of Grace they are ſhed forth by the Spirit from him upon all the members and manifeſt to our ſenſe: all things of the firſt Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion were made by Chriſt, all things pertaining to the ſecond are ceaſed in him; thus Redemption is firſt entire in him, afterwards in meaſures revealed in his, a work once perfected for ever in him, not to be done by peices in us; and ſo it is in being and finiſhed already, but hid with Chriſt in God.</p>
               <p>Now upon theſe heavenly things there is a vail, whereby they are hid, the law in the conſcience, Reaſon and ſenſe in the fleſh, and there is an evidence whereby they are ſeen, that is, Faith; unto ſuch as are under this vail nothing is ſeen nor heard but the Commandments to work, and the ſentences of death where work is not; the Law in the letter, and deeds in the fleſh, as the face of the covering ſpread upon the heart that Chriſt cannot be ſeen: the higheſt divinity of men in this ſtate is this Perfection by obedience to the letter without, or at the beſt to the Spirit within; Chriſt as a Law-giver in their Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and a worker of it in their Perſons, not as a Saviour having once fulfilled it for them in himſelf: what of God is felt and wrought in themſelves, that they beleive, and by that Rule they judge, while the unſpeakable righteouſneſs, operation and life hid in Chriſt, and with him reſerved in God, with the faith, liberty, joy and peace thereof is hid from their eyes; ſuch is the vail and the people there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
               <p>But where Faith is come the vail is done away, the earthly man with his deeds and death, his hopes and fears, and all things belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him are ſeen to be aboliſhed and overcome by the everlaſting
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:48979:7"/> righteouſneſs and Spirit of Life that is in Chriſt, even as the night is overcome by the day; and this is to be underſtood to be true in him, a Covenant in him, ordered in all things and ſure to us, not alwayes perceived in feeling to our earthly members, yet ſeen and fulfilled in the inward man through faith.</p>
               <p>It is ſaid, 2 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 5.7. <hi>We walk by faith not by ſight:</hi> Faith and ſight are to be underſtood, either as they are perfecting each other, or as by men divided and made contrary one to the other; ſight of God has a glory and ſweetneſs; faith in him, though not ſo ſeen, has a certainty and evidence; faith beholds things as true in Chriſt, though hid to ſenſe and feeling; ſight knows them onely as ſhining or flaming forth upon the heart: viſions and revelations bring joy and comfort, but they are things that go and come, and the breathings of the Spirit may blow when they liſt, but when theſe ſtreams are withheld and as paſſed away, yet he ever lives, and we alſo in him: God ſpake in times paſt with the Fathers and Prophets by viſions to ſenſe; he ſpeaks in theſe laſt times in his Son to faith: vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions by figure, as thoſe were, they were but given at times and paſſed away; the face of Jeſus Chriſt beheld by faith is the conſtant and ſtanding viſion now under the Goſpel: ſpiritual influences and act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings do yeild ſome reflection, and viſion of God, but as a Man ſees his face in a troubled water, broken and changeable; but the face of Chriſt as the Chriſtal and ſtill waters preſents God alwayes in his clear and bleſſed Image as full of Grace and Truth: they who put ſpiritual workings for the Grace that is in Chriſt, and a ſenſe of the ſpirit for faith in him, they do under a pretence of Spirit deſtroy Chriſt Jeſus, they take away that Goſpel which preſents us in him before any work done, our perfection, our Sabbath, our Reſt, and leads us to work again for perfection by obedience to the Light within, that is, by the Law.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Faith and Sight.</head>
               <p>FAith and ſight, the Goſpel-Chriſtian is for both in their ſeaſon and place; all other Religions have divided them and erred; as it is very obſervable, that ſight being alone, that is, ſight of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head without faith in Chriſt has been &amp; is the foundation of all falſe, fancied and Idolatrous worſhips that are named: fight of the deity by the things that are made is the higheſt Religion of Philoſophers and Pagans; ſight of God by the Golden Calfe, by the Idols of gld
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:48979:8"/> and ſilver was the idolatry of Iſrael in the wilderneſs and <hi>Canaan:</hi> Conceiving the things of the Spirit of God by the ſight and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of natural Reaſon is the foundation of <hi>Arminians,</hi> a Sect of Morality, and of <hi>Socinians</hi> a Sect of ſubtilty: a Kingdom with ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation and fair ſhews in the fleſh to the ſight without, was the Religion of Phariſees and legal Goſpellers: ſome are of a weaker ſpirit, their Religion is about things of ſight, touch not, taſte not; ſome are of ſtronger heads, ſuch are for divinations of the brain, things ſeen to Reaſon; babes in Chriſt are for enlightnings and taſts, and gifts, things of ſight to the inward ſenſe; and they that would ſeem to be the higheſt, are for all to be known and beleived as done onely within: thus nothing is leſs learned and underſtood by the moſt of Religions and Opinions that are, than faith in Chriſt, and the life of faith: ſenſe, or reaſon, or fancy, or myſtical legalitie, (all which in the account of the Spirit are but ſight and appearance) ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving left no more room for true Goſpel faith, than onely in that Church of the faithful that holds the Head, even him that is far above all things and they in him by faith.</p>
               <p>And hence it is, that where ſight or ſenſe as to ſpiritual things is by any ſpirit or doctrine made a principle and rule of judgement, theſe and ſuch like concluſions follow; do this and live; if thou ſinneſt after faith, thou art under the law; ſo much obedience, ſo far juſtified; while fleſh luſteth within thee, no freedom from ſin; to be perfectly juſtified by Chriſt and reconciled to God is not till fully mortified and obedient to Chriſt within thee, all which are ſentences of the Law, not of Grace, denying Chriſt, overwhelming the afflicted in ſorrow without hope, and turning the feet of the lame out of the way; of ſuch doctrines beware.</p>
               <p>On the other hand, where faith, or things not ſeen, or things in Chriſt are made the rule or principle of Judgement, theſe ſayings are bleſſed and true; I am black but comely; as dying and behold we live; when I am weak then am I ſtrong, <hi>Enoch, Noah</hi> and <hi>Abraham</hi> dyed in the faith, yet received not the promiſes, onely ſaw them afar off; all things are put in ſubjection under Chriſt, though we ſee not all things yet put under him.</p>
               <p>The ſum of all is, meaſure not things by ſight but faith; the door of faith is open when that of ſenſe may be ſhut; rejoyce alwayes in the Lord, though thou mayeſt not alwayes ſee him: ſight as alone is the foundation of idolatry, if thou beeſt led by that, thou falleſt back into the Law, though in a myſtery of deceit; if thou walkeſt by faith,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:48979:8"/> thou ſhalt be led on to ſight, not that of reaſon or dry ſpeculation, but of ſpiritual, ſweet and gracious mainfeſtation of Chriſt, as in perſon a Saviour for thee, and as in Spirit revealing himſelf in thee: and hereby their ſecond principle above named of juſtification and redemption to be the light within, as obeyed within may appear to be a myſtery of iniquity to my underſtanding, affirming in effect, that Chriſt is divided, <hi>Paul</hi> and every Chriſtian crucified and made an offering for himſelf, and thereby juſtified, reconciled and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; and if it be ſo, let this people conſider and fear; but if not ſo, let plainneſs of ſpeech be uſed and not a vail.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the Spirit and Scriptures as together making up a perfect witneſs or rule of faith.</head>
               <p>COncerning the Scriptures, paſſing by all other diſtinctions; they are firſt, the Law of Commandments ordained by Angels, a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the letter anſwering to that of God in every man, the law in the conſcience; this within and that without being one in ſubſtance, a light and a law of things to be done for righteouſneſs and life; thus all Nations have received a law, having a law in themſelves, though ſuppreſſed and vailed; thus all have a law, though dimmed and darkened, pointing to the righteouſneſs of the law or firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> but not attaining thereunto: and herein all Nations are one, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Jews, Turks or Pagans, their Light one, Law one, Religion one, all following one righteouſneſs, that is, of the Law; onely in diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of notion, and form, and manner of worſhip; all equally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded under the law of ſin, and all equally ignorant of the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> and righteouſneſs by him: thus if Scriptures were not, by that Candle in man God might be known, and the law and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, yet but as in a miniſtration of death: the righteouſneſs of God, and the law of the Spirit, and God manifeſt in fleſh being a myſtery hid from the natural man, declared onely by the Goſpel, and diſcerned by the Spirit.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The word of the Goſpel or Reconciliation being the joyful tidings of an heavenly Perſon and an heavenly gift, both equally wonderful, God manifeſt in fleſh, and our righteouſneſs in him; in whom old things, or things belonging to the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> whether the Law of God, or deeds of the fleſh are paſſed away, having in him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived their period or perfection, and all things, though not yet to us fully ſeen, in him become new.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:48979:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Thus the Goſpel being a myſtery of things hid in Chriſt, is neither written not to be ſeen in the heart of man; and being a myſtery of things of the new Creature, and of another world, cannot be known by the wiſdom of this world, that is, by the wiſdom, ſpirit and light of the natural Man: as he that gave a law to all the world, has ſet in every man a light to know that law; ſo the miniſtration of Grace being a far other thing, and exceeding it in glory, cannot be known but by a far other Light than that in every man and exceeding it in glory, that is the Spirit of grace. Wherefore the bringing the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel to Light is after this manner; it firſt lay hid in God, unknown to Angels or men, as the deeps that are beneath; afterward was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared and adminiſtred by the Word made fleſh in the Perſon of Chriſt, as the ſpring head bring forth the deeps beneath, thereby him revealed through the ſending of the Spirit to them that were with him, and to this day by the ſame ſpirit to them that beleive through their word: and hence theſe things follow.</p>
               <p>That the knowledge of God according to the law all Nations may have by his enlightening within them; the myſtery of God in Chriſt not ſo, the firſt being engraven in the ſpirit of man, this having not ſo much as entered into the heart of man, and being onely revealed by another Light far exceeding in glory, even that Spirit which the world never ſaw nor can receive.</p>
               <p>That the Scriptures as joyned in one are the onely ſufficient, war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted and ſtanding evidence of Chriſt to men; the Scriptures as the Image of him without, and the Spirit as the light ſhining upon them, bring forth the true and living image of him into the heart: if Grace have appeared to any, where Scriptures are not, the Spirit is free to blow where he liſts, but this ſpirit or grace the light in the natural man, knows nothing of.</p>
               <p>That the Spirit and Scriptures together, as they are a full witneſs to Chriſt and Truth, ſo they are as the ſtanding Oracle or conſtant Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, unto which all ought to come for the knowledge of Truth, the perfect Judge for ending all difference about ſpiritual matters, and the perfect Rule for tryal of all ſpirits and wayes of Religion; the Scriptures as the lanthorn, and the Spirit as the candle therein; they as the Commandment of Chriſt to his Church, and the Spirit as the Judge giving the true underſtanding thereof, and bringing forth the Myſtery and Majeſty that lies hid therein.</p>
               <p>Either of theſe, if ſet up aſunder without the other, brings forth a twofold errour, both perillous and hurtful.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:48979:9"/>1. Impoſing the letter of Scripture without the light of the Spirit, whether by Churches or Councils, may be an oppoſing the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures againſt the Spirit, and ſets up another dominion over the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, which is ſubject to Chriſt alone.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Impoſing any thing for viſion or Spirit without liberty of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal, or reference to Scripture, whether by an Angel from heaven, or an Apoſtle, is a ſhaking mens minds from off the foundation of the Apoſtles and Prophets, Jeſus Chriſt being the chief corner ſtone, and a carrying them away as by a blaſt of wind unto another Jeſus, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Spirit, of whom God never ſpake: he that impoſeth any thing upon conſcience for Spirit without teſtimony of Scripture, is as he that impoſeth for Scripture without teſtimony of the Spirit; both equally ſeeking to bear dominion over our faith: the ſecond errour, if either, is worſe than the firſt; the generations that are paſt, who lived more in the letter, ſuffered much by the firſt; theſe laſt times, which profeſs more of the Spirit, may ſuffer an hour of ſore temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the laſt.</p>
               <p>The concluſion is; A call to any light, or voyce, or word within, as the way to Chriſt, from the Spirit and Scriptures; unto ſpirits in diſtemper, who take apparitions of the night for dawnings of day, the ſparklings of fancy for the true beams of faith, unto ſuch th<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s may ſeem a miniſtry of light; but he that through Grace has ſtill the faith of Jeſus, knows it to be a foundation of Sathan laid in the deep, in order to a deſign of blotting out the Goſpel, and therein the face of the Mediator, the Church in him, their liberty, their joyes and ſongs in Chriſt: and hereby their third principle aforeſaid, affirming the Light in the Conſcience the way or guide to Chriſt, whereto one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to attend, appears to be a darkſome, fleſhly and moſt legal Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, a very grave, wherein Chriſt, Redemption, Attonement, our Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, and Triumph, and Sabbath in him lies buried, deſpiſed and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten for ever: thus according to my meaſure, their main Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples are weighed, let the ſpiritual judge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Light in all men, what it is, and of what uſe.</head>
               <p>THere is one thing more which I may not paſs, as being the ſoul and life of all their principles, that the light which is in every man is Chriſt the Redeemer, the Spirit, a twofold errour may be diſcerned herein by the things following. Chriſt as in the beginning, the Word, was he by whom all things pertaining to the firſt Creation or natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:48979:10"/> man were made and do conſiſt; and ſo he was and is the fountain of being and life to every Creature, in him we live and breath.</p>
               <p>Chriſt, as the Word by whom all things were made, is the ſplendour and image of the inviſible God to the firſt Creation; as brightneſs to the Son, ſo Chriſt to the Father, is a face of light ſending forth his lightenings upon every Creature, as a Rule or Law to every motion and operation; and as thus, he hath lighted up a candle in the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral mans heart, and alſo preſents ſome beams of the Godhead, and therein of juſtice, equity, ſoberneſs, &amp;c, to be diſcerned by his can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, and obſerved as his law: thus all natural principles, moral ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and juſt laws of Nations, are beams from Chriſt, as he is the Word and Light of God to the natural man, not as he is a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer.</p>
               <p>The higheſt office and uſe of this Light within, or of the natural man, is this, to receive from God the manifeſtation of the inviſible things of him, that is, the divine power and Godhead, and to return to God obedience thereto juſt and perfect, as God is juſt and perfect, that is, to know him as God, and glorifie him as God: thus the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt account of the light within every man, according to the Spirit and Scriptures, is this; as in it ſelf it is the work of the Law written in their hearts; as to its object, it is the candle of the Lord in the Spirit of man, beholding God according to ſome ſpeculations of the divinity, knowing nothing of the precious Goſpel Myſtery, God ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt in fleſh; and as to its exerciſe, it is a doing by nature the things contained in the law: hence as the ſum of things ſpoken theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions follow.</p>
               <p>That the Light within for matter and ſubſtance is the fame with the law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> that was written upon tables of ſtone, this upon tables of fleſh in the conſcience; both were given for tranſgreſſion, not for righteouſneſs; neither of them could reveal or give life, both Jews and Gentiles being all under ſin. From both theſe Laws, whether in tables of ſtone or tables of conſcience, Chriſt came to juſtifie and deliver, bringing forth in himſelf inſtead of both a more excellent and perfect law, as far as the Sun of Righteouſneſs himſelf excels that which is but a beam or letter of righteouſneſs onely: ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>J. Naylor</hi> and the people of that way, Chriſt came to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem Iſrael in the fleſh from the Law and every letter without, but to eſtabliſh in force that within in the conſcience, by obedience unto which men come to be redeemed: this is the firſt errour; the Light within or work of the Law in the heart, from the terrour and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:48979:10"/> whereof the bleſſed Lord Jeſus came to deliver, is called and worſhipped by them as the Redeemer and Spirit.</p>
               <p>Secondly, while they affirm the light within, or in every man, is the Redeemer, they know Chriſt onely as a Law-giver and worker, not as a Juſtifier and Saviour; naturally, according to the Godhead, as judging and purging away ſins within them, not Evangelically, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that bleſſed union or marriage with the humanity, as having already therein purged away all ſins by himſelf.</p>
               <p>Chriſt is formed in the minds, and deſcribed in the writings of men under a twofold image or reſemblance; one according to Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel myſtery by the Spirit of God, the other according to natural Reaſon by the ſpirit of this world: Chriſt beheld as having our ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful fleſh, condemnation and death as a garment upon him, and as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving rent and torn the ſame from off him again by the power of the Spirit of life in him, and having ſo taken them all away, as if they had never been; this is a true reſemblance of him; thus is he ſeen in his proper colours; thus Chriſt is no <hi>Moſes,</hi> no Exactor, no giver of Laws, but a moſt ſweet Saviour and giver of Grace, thus is he nothing elſe but infinite Mercy and Goodneſs, freely given, and freely giving to us all things in himſelf; Chriſt according to this form ſhining in thy faith, ſhall put to flight Armies of thy temptations, ſhall try the Spirits, ſhall preſerve thee from being ſpoiled by any falſe doctrines, either of ſubtil philoſophy, or ſpecious Legality, if this image of him thou ſuffereſt to be defaced, or any other wayes painted out unto thee, when the hour of temptation or trouble cometh, thou ſhalt ſoon be overthrown.</p>
               <p>By the Spirit of this world Chriſt is ſet forth under another reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance, by ſome more according to the Godhead, as the Word, the Light, the Truth, the Spirit; by others according to the humanity, as a man holy, ſpotleſs, ſeparate from ſinners, and by both as a living exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple unto the world of perfect obedience to the law of the Spirit and the life of God; this ſets forth Chriſt indeed as a divine Perſon and ſo has a Truth, but preſents him onely as giving a Law and working it in us, and ſo denies and blots out the Glory of his Grace, as being the end of the Law: this is the divinity of Sophiſters and Juſtitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and all that they know or can teach of Chriſt; let ſuch Teachers know, who cry up the Spirit to cry down the bloud, who teach him as an Example and caſt out the Attonement, let all ſuch know, while they vaunt of ſublime divinity and myſterious truth, they do but ſet Chriſt in <hi>Moſes</hi> chair as Law-giver and Judge, but the great love in him as
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:48979:11"/> propitiation for ſins, they know nothing of: the higheſt Religion of natural Reaſon, is to pierce far into notions of God, and to ſet him before it as a pattern to obey; but faith onely ſees the deep ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret of Grace laid up in a crucified Chriſt: he that would behold the glory of God, and would be ſet up in thoſe heavenly places, let him lay down his Reaſon how heightened ſoever, and begin in the ſimplicity of faith at the crucified body of Chriſt, in whom he ſhall ſee himſelf dead, and buried, and raiſed up alſo together with him, not by any work or obedience to Chriſt within, but by the faith of the operation of God, who hath raiſed Chriſt from the dead.</p>
               <p>Hence theſe things follow. 1. That the Light within, or of the natural man, with the work of Reaſon together, is that ſpirit of this world, which hath formed this falſe reſemblance of Chriſt as a Law-giver, and Worker, and Pattern; as upon the Croſs, an Attonement to Juſtice, the victory of ſin, curſe and the grave, and the Head over all (which is the true likeneſs or image of him, terrible to others, but the joy of his own) ſo he is not known to the Light within. If a man ſhould be born into the world, and in the ſpace of one hour ſhould grow up to the perfection of a man, to the fulneſs of Light and Reaſon, propound unto him theſe doctrines whether he will chuſe, that Chriſt has already by himſelf purged away his ſins, and ſanctified him for ever before any good work wrought in him; or that not Chriſt without, but the Light within him is the Chriſt, which through obedience thereto purges away ſin in him, and redeems him that way; the firſt would ſeem fooliſhneſs and a contradiction to his Light, the laſt would be received as the more reaſonable and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent way.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That this falſe conception or reſemblance of Chriſt as a Law-giver and Worker is an Idol, and the root of idolatrous Religions: doctrines of Circumciſion added to Chriſt by the falſe Apoſtles; of charity, humility and bodily chaſtiſements by the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> preparatives before faith by the Teachers of the Law; and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Light within, as the way of Redemption, by the people called Quakers: all theſe, though divers as to Parties and Notions, yet are one in the root and foundation of their faith, all looking up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Chriſt, according to the Law, as perfecting out in part or in whole Redemption by work within them. Conceptions of Chriſt, how divine ſoever, if not as crucified for our offences, and raiſed up again for our juſtification, are but Idols ſet up of a more ſpiritual
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:48979:11"/> nature, as the Gods of Gold and Silver</p>
               <p>Laſtly, That they who affirm the Light in every man that condemns of ſin to be Chriſt, the Redeemer, have ſet up an Idol for Chriſt, they are gone back from that Chriſt that came not to judge but to ſave the world, that ſpeaks not condemnation, but meer joy and ſweetneſs to the weary and weak, and have ſet up another Jeſus, and another Goſpel, neither of which, nor the worſhippers thereof, ſhall be able to ſtand when the true Jeſus ſhall appear; this is the other errour as to the Light within.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Two things charged upon us by this people: firſt, that we deny the Light within, and ſet it againſt Chriſt, weighed and removed.</head>
               <p>THis bleſſed doctrine of Grace, Chriſt bearing away ſins as in his crucified body, and juſtifying the ungodly as in himſelf, is by the words and writings of this people often and principally charged of two things 1. As denying the Light within, and ſetting it againſt Chriſt. 2. As teaching Chriſt at a diſtance, and onely without: A word to both may not be unſeaſonable. While the Light within con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns of ſin, to beleive by Chriſt, I am juſtified from ſin, is not this to make the light within againſt Chriſt? no, no more than the Law is againſt the Promiſe; the Light in the Conſcience and the Law of Commandements for ſubſtance are one, their power one, their kingdom one, that is, the fleſh or firſt <hi>Adam;</hi> Jeſus Chriſt came forth one greater than the Law, greater than our Conſcience: againſt him aroſe the Law of commandments, the Law in the conſcience, ſin in the fleſh, death and the curſe, all great and mighty Lords, who had devoured the earth, ſparing no fleſh, neither Kings, Princes, nor People, whom he having vanquiſhed and triumphed openly over them, he took the Law out of the tables, the work of the Law out of the heart, and ſin out of the fleſh, as the Conquerour takes the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered Kings out of the Throne of their Kingdoms, and nailed them to his Croſs: according to the fleſh, he was, as it were, given for a prey to the fowls of Heaven, and the beaſts on Earth, principalities on high, and the miſeries of the fleſh: according to the Spirit of glory and power, he redeemed the prey, brought back the ſpoil, raiſed up his fleſh, and therein his body myſtical, and gathered together all things that were againſt him, that are againſt us, buried them in his grave, and therein ſhut them up for ever.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:48979:12"/>
               <p>Hence then a beleiver is divided into twain, and accordingly lives in two Kingdoms, according to his faith he is a man in Chriſt, raiſed in him, and ſet up in him above the law of his fleſh, of conſcience or ſin, above the whole world, with all things therein, into the glorious liberty and bleſſedneſs of Jeſus Chriſt; as thus he is to be known no more after the fleſh, but as having put it off in union with Chriſt; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to reaſon and ſenſe he is a man in the fleſh, ſubject to the Law, to infirmity and death, the life of his ſpiritual man being many times hid from the ſenſe of his natural, as the Life of Chriſt in the Godhead was ſometimes hid from his fleſh.</p>
               <p>According to this twofold ſtate a beleiver is under, he does at the ſame time give a twofold account of himſelf, both juſt and true; in my body indeed I have a law of ſin, but as I am in the Lord I have put it off; as I walk by ſight I am in the earth, in labours, in groan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, warfare and imperfection; but as I walk by faith, I am in heaven, received into glory, walking on my high-places in Reſt, in victory and perfection, where I ſhut my eyes from looking upon my ſelf, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get all my fears, infirmities and bondage, leaving them all behind me as under my feet; and ſo is that word fulfilled in him, as ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful yet alway rejoycing, as having nothing, and yet poſſeſſiing all things.</p>
               <p>This is ſome of the myſtery and knowledge of Chriſt crucified, not like unto that of the Schools and Law-makers, whoſe higheſt know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge therein comes to no more but this, that the Humanity on the Croſs reſigned up it ſelf in profound humility and meekneſs to the will of the Divinity, as the Popiſh Doctors, or that he yeilded perfect obedience to the Light within him, for a living example to the world, as this people called Quakers: I ſay, this knowledge and ſuch preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Croſs of Chriſt are poor, barren and empty, reaching onely to the morality thereof, the praiſes of a juſt man dying with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe, and of his ſpirit and temper; but not diſcerning the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry therein, that is, an end put to the Law, to ſin and the fleſh, to and upon all them that are given to him: thus their firſt charge is weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and reſolved in this, that to a man in Chriſt, the Light within accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of ſin, pertains onely to the fleſh, and ſhould abide in the fleſh; that Chriſt alone as juſtifying from ſins, as joy and ſweetneſs, ſhould abide in the conſcience as the chamber of the Bridegroom and Bride, into which no Law, nor Light, nor any thing that accuſeth, may in any wiſe enter, Chriſt raigning therein over every Law; thus accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the fleſh and light within, there is conſcience for ſin in the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:48979:12"/> juſtified man, according to faith and union with Chriſt there is no more conſcience of ſins, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.2.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Second thing charged, That we beleive in a Chriſt without, and at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, weighed and reſolved.</head>
               <p>THe other charge follows, that to beleive Chriſt has redeemed us as in his own body without, is to beleive in a Chriſt without and at a diſtance: this charge examined will appear to be vain: the faith of the Goſpel ſaith, that Chriſt deſcended into our nature, and therein came down to us in our bloud, our priſons, under judgement, and thence raiſed us up together with himſelf into the heavenly pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; he deſcended firſt into the lower parts of the earth, into the loweſt eſtate of loſt and undone ſinners, and thence aſcended up far above all Heavens, and raiſed us up together in himſelf; this ſets forth Chriſt as near, and not at a diſtance, as one within us, wrapped in our ſin, as our ſin, and us as one with him in Righteouſneſs, and his very righteouſneſs; oh the bleſſed nearneſs between him and the beleiver.</p>
               <p>That Chriſt comes down in Spirit into our Perſons, not to redeem, but to manifeſt the Redemption, not as a light accuſing of ſin, but as revealing righteouſneſs and liberty from ſin in himſelf, and gathering us out of the life of reaſon and ſenſe, the law and things without, into the glorious reſt and victory in himſelf; he there lets us know, that we are in him his Siſter and Spouſe, that he is in us our Head and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and that all things are ours, that we are Chriſts, and that Chriſt is Gods: Thus Chriſt is beheld both as without, having wrought all things for us, in the Perſon of the Mediatour, and alſo as within us, working all our works in us as a quickening Spirit.</p>
               <p>On the other hand, the faith of the Quakers, ſo called, ſayes thus; that Chriſt indeed took on him our nature, but not our judgement and ſin, that he dyed at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> but by way of example, not as a ſacrifice putting away ſin; that he did not the work by himſelf at that once, but onely ſhewed us the way how he redeems within us in every generation.</p>
               <p>That Chriſt is come in our fleſh, but as a light accuſing and judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, renewing a law, and requiring obedience thereto through the fire and the ſword, by them called the bloud of the croſs, and ſo through perfect obedience juſtifying and redeeming. O what dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and confuſion has covered this people, thus to make faith void, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:48979:13"/> the bloud of Chriſt of none effect, and now let the ſpiritual-wiſe judge, unto whom Chriſt is known, as nigh, or as afar off, to them, or to us: to us who behold him as having already ſcattered the clouds of the law and darkneſs, dryed up the flouds of ſin and death, opened a way into the Holieſt, and received us into his glory; and beſides all this, ſhewing himſelf in the neareſt conjunctions and freindlieſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances of a Brother, a Father, and Husband, after an unſpeakable manner filling us with his fulneſs: or to them, who draw the vail over this moſt comfortable face and aſpect of things, ſet up the law, ſin and death again to be ſuffered, ſatisfied and done away within us, and Chriſt ſtanding upon terms with us of obedience and death, without which no remiſſion of ſins, no redemption, nor benefit to be expected from him: I ſay, let the wiſe judge, who of theſe have Chriſt moſt nigh, moſt as unvailed, in the moſt inward and freindly way: let the charge then of Chriſt without return from whence it came.</p>
               <p>I ſhall onely mind ye of the Parable of the wounded man lying between <hi>Jericho</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> there came firſt a Prieſt and a Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite, looked on him and paſſed by; after came a Samaritane, had compaſſion and bound up his wounds, putting in oyle and wine, ſet him on his own beaſt, and brought him to an Inn, and took care of him there: according to the ſevere and unmerciful doctrine of this people, Jeſus Chriſt came down into our nature, beheld it wounded and lying in bloud, able enough to have ſaid to us, while in our bloud, live, and to have made us ſo; but onely leaving us an example of perfection and ſufferings, wherein, if we followed him, we ſhould live, and ſo departed, leaving us as he found us, till the Light within come and cured us; ſo they reckon of the Man Chriſt to be ſuch a one as was the Preiſt or Levite: but bleſſed be that Goſpel that ſaies, he paſſed by, beheld us in bloud, and it was a time of love; with the bloud of his Humanity, and the love and glory of his Godhead, he bathed our wounds, ſuppled and healed them, and after ſet us upon his own beaſt, carried us to the Inn, bare us in his body, and carried us into his Manſion in the Fathers houſe; according as it is ſaid, <hi>He hath born our griefs, carried our ſorrows, for he was wounded for our tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, and bruiſed for our iniquities, the chaſtiſements of our peace was upon him, and by his ſtripes we are healed:</hi> This ſets forth Chriſt to be the kind Samaritane, the neighbour nigheſt unto us; the other makes him unmerciful, going afar off, not tarrying with us.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:48979:13"/>
               <head>What is the inward Life, and who is the retired Chriſtian.</head>
               <p>THis gives occaſion, among other matters, to caſt in a word con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concerning the inward life or retired Chriſtian; as all other ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual things, ſo this has its truth and its counterfeit, by miſtake where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of of one for the other, the faith may be perverted and our minds ſoon ſhaken.</p>
               <p>Separation from the world, the company of men and affairs of this life, in ſtilneſs and ſilence ſearching into the knowledge of my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, the divine being and things of the inward world, was the Religion of ſome Jeſuites, School-men and others; that ſuperſtition in the Conſcience and fancy in the Head was all in this, may appear by their writings, which are filled either with perplexities of wit, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural ſpeculations of God, or rules of Legality, leading men unto God by a perfection of obedience, Chriſt crucified as the way into the Holieſt being not known unto them; theſe had but a ſhew of the inward life, for they entered not by faith within the vail.</p>
               <p>Retirement from the Scriptures and adminiſtrations without, from Religions and Aſſemblies, from all order and form, profeſſed and practiſed by whomſoever, unto the Light within, and to it alone to attend, as to the onely Scripture, the voyce of God and light of men, without reſpect to perſon or work, Redeemer or Redemption with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, this is the Religion of the people called Quakers: they who by the Light within peirced into inviſible things, the eternal Power and Godhead had but the wiſdom of this world, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.20 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 1.20. and were of the world under ſin as all other; again, they who excelled in ſhews of humility, wiſdom and all outward holineſs, as to the exerciſe of the body, and neglecting the ſame, yet their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion was no more than the Rudiments of this world and periſhing Ordinances, <hi>Col,</hi> 2. I muſt ſay the ſame of this people and their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, to be both of this world, until they give faith or acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the fleſh or dead body of Chriſt to be the onely way into the inward life or within the vail; which whilſt they deny, inſtead of bringing into Heaven, into the peace of God, and reſt from their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, they ſhut up the Kingdom, and keep men on earth to perform ſacrifices and obedience in fleſh for their attonement; theſe have a pretence to the inward life, but are not entered through the vail of his fleſh by faith into the Holieſt.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:48979:14"/>
               <p>He that by faith goes out of all things in himſelf, whether perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Reaſon, or the Light in the Conſcience into Jeſus Chriſt cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, and in him beleives, all things of Law or Nature, with the works of both, to be paſſed away, and himſelf crucified, and waſhed, and perfected for ever; and not conſidering his body now dead, nor yet the deadneſs of all things as to any good in his fleſh, but ſhutting his eye and ear from all things of ſenſe and reaſon in the world or his fleſh, cleaves onely by faith to the dead body of Chriſt, and therewith mounts up into the ſpirit of his mind into Chriſt Jeſus alone as his own victory, righteouſneſs and life, this man is he that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters into Reſt, into the inward life; he is truly ſeparate from all the Religions of the world, and yet exerciſes a Religion in the world, he is free from all men, and yet a ſervant unto all; his life is in the Head, while decayes and deaths in his fleſh; and of him is that true, he is as unknown, and yet well known. This is the retired Chriſtian, that moſt truly lives and rejoyces in things not ſeen to ſenſe nor rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, nor the light in the natural man; he has the cleareſt, ſureſt and ſweeteſt beams of Chriſt, leading him not into Phariſaical auſterity, nor wanton libertiniſme, but into a ſpirit of holineſs, quietneſs and ſtilneſs in the Lord, yet ſo as that, according to grace received, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to become all things to all men.</p>
               <p>The<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e is a generation who have the form of faith and knowledge, of the words and profeſſion of Chriſt, but have not the faith whereby they are dead in Chriſt, and he lives in them; it ſufficeth them to know Chriſt dyed for ſins, which faith is common to all men; but the myſtery of faith they have not, that is, union with him in it, or that they are buried with him into death in the fleſh, and raiſed up with him into life in the ſpirit; they behold Chriſt as without to be the end of the law, of ſin and death, the fulneſs and fulfilling of all things in himſelf, wherein they do well and taſt ſome joy therein; but they receive him not by faith into themſelves: my root and foundation is this, what Chriſt is and has done without me in himſelf, but the way to partake of the benefit of it is my union with him; theſe do confeſs to the truth of the firſt, but are not joyned to it by union with it, and ſo fail in the laſt. Chriſt indeed is by theſe honoured onely as without, while in his Spirit and Grace he is by luſt crucified with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: from ſuch do ye turn away.</p>
               <p>Another generation there is, not beleiving the end of ſin in the death of Chriſt, nor themſelves perfected onely in the Head, look for a Redemption, not that already in being in Jeſus Chriſt, but to be
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:48979:14"/> wrought out by him in their own perſons; that is, after the example of Chriſt, turning away from all things inwardly and outwardly, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thought, deſire, pleaſure or affection and every creature, till they come to the Light and Being of God, and become ſo paſſive, and in all things ſubject thereto, that God may do all things in them: A cheif Maſter of this way ſpeaks plainly thus; <hi>Though God ſhould aſſume all men that are unto himſelf, and ſhould become Man in them, and they in him ſhould become God, and the ſame ſhould not be done in me, my fall ſhould never be recovered nor yet my ſin done away, except the ſame were alſo done in me:</hi> Theſe are the words of a Germain Prieſt, written (as is ſaid) above two hundred and fifty years ago: this doctrine, as it carries upon it the notion of God or the divine Nature doing all in us, has a ſhew of glory, but as it denies that God has done all things for us in Chriſt, ſo it has no glory, but rather ſpreads again the vail which Chriſt rent in his bloud, that the riches and glory of grace may not appear: if any of the fiery darts of hell have ever been ſhot againſt the ſaith whereby I ſtand, and if by any of them I have ever been near to ſtaggering, this doctrine was one: if Scriptures and a crucified Jeſus may ſtand for a little aſide, among all the doctrines either named or profeſſed this day among men, for ſhews of light, ſpirituality and holineſs, I know none to be compared with this; yet if I much miſtake not, the glorious and eternal effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, victory and triumph of the Son of God upon the Croſs over the whole world and all things againſt us, is by none ſo much obſcured and debaſed as by this; of which I think it meet at beſt in this place to ſay onely this, that if the ſins, tranſgreſſions and evils of mankind were ſo great before God, that all the wood of <hi>Lebanon,</hi> all the Rams of <hi>Nebaioth,</hi> ten thouſand rivers of oyle, and the firſt born of our body, were not ſufficient to offer for the ſin of our ſoul, that the bloud of Jeſus, and in him the eternal wiſdom and righteouſneſs of God was found onely among all things in heaven and earth to be ſufficient to take away the ſame; then let all high thoughts come down where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by any do or ſhall exalt themſelves into an equal capacity with Chriſt Jeſus of drinking that cup, and being baptiſed with that baptiſme in the meaſure and manner as he did, in hope to make that attonement for their own ſins, which onely could be made once by Chriſt never to be renewed more: wherefore coming to God through the bloud of Jeſus, beholding the glory of God in the ſafe of Chriſt, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God in the Spirit of Chriſt, this is the true inward Life; but he that enters in any other way, may break through
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:48979:15"/> unto the Lord and gaze, but he ſhall periſh.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A twofold departure from the faith in the laſt dayes: what the firſt is.</head>
               <p>NOw the things hitherto ſpoken off give occaſion to admoniſh you of a twofold departure that ſhould come to paſs in the laſt dayes; the one of men holding the form of godlineſs, but denying the power thereof, 2 <hi>Tim</hi> 3 the other of men denying the form of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or of the words of faith and good doctrine, but pretending to the power thereof, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1, 2, 6. ſeducing ſpirits &amp; worldly intereſts mingling themſelves with the Goſpel and Church of Chriſt, have in every Age ſince the Apoſtles fell aſleep, been as the two Armes of the God of this world; with the one he has defaced and vailed the image and glory of Chriſt in Goſpel-truths, with the other he has quenched the love of Chriſt and the power of godlineſs in the hearts of men.</p>
               <p>The one of theſe defections is to be ſeen at this day in this our Nation, in degrees of wickedneſs beyond what has happened in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer generations; namely in the Army, their Leader and Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, their Court and Clergy, with all their ſtupified admirers and ſervants, who have ſometimes been as the ſword of the Lord, as the Chariot of fire, wherein our Lord Jeſus has ridden forth againſt the intereſts of uſurpation and tyranny, and againſt his and his peoples enemies in this Nation, this was their miniſtry, the eyes of their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings enlightened with beams from the face of Chriſt; their hearts as burning coals conſuming them with zeal to Chriſt; their hands ſtretched up towards heaven to receive him coming; their feet with wings ſetting them up upon the Head of all worldly and lower intereſts to prepare the way of the Lord, this was their ſpirit and poſture: againſt the whole kingdom of Anti-chriſt, both in its forms and powers, either in the civil or ſpiritual ſtate, went forth their pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, profeſſions and undertakings, the ſound whereof went abroad almoſt through all the earth; from off them is this Spirit of glory and vertue departed, and in the place thereof it entered another ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, feirce, ruling the people by laws and weapons of warre, inſtead of pure, ſpiritual righteouſneſs and meekneſs: without natural affection peircing the hearts with unkindneſs, and the ſides with ſufferings, of them who have been as a Mother that bore and nouriſhed them with their own bloud, life and ſpirit all the dayes of their youth, while they
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:48979:15"/> were little in their own, and deſpiſed in the worlds eyes: blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, thinking, ſpeaking and meaſuring evil to that ſpirit of faith, light and expectation in others, which they had taſted and teſtified of formerly in themſelves: traytors, betraying that Right and liberty, the price of much precious bloud, the ſuccouring and defence where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was committed to their truſt unto the will and pleaſure of unlimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Monarchy: heady, proud, high minded, impoſing laws, conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions, powers, forming, transforming all things in the ſpiritual and civil intereſts, in a way of ſuperiority and maſterſhip above and apart from others, without taking in the hopeful aſſiſtances of more light, by the conjunction of the counſels, hearts and hands of their ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times dear brethren unto themſelves, as if the Spirit of the Lord came forth onely from them, or came onely into them: incontinent, not behaving themſelves towards the wife of their youth, the new <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> to which they are joyned as one fleſh, and one ſpirit, but have poured out themſelves upon every one that paſſeth by: unholy and prophane, defiling their holy things, the appearances and gifts of Chriſt, the buddings, beginnings and earneſts of a more excellent way both in Church and State, by mingling them with a ſtrange ſeed, the dark and fleſhly principles, policies and adminiſtrations of worldly Reaſon and Prudence: deſpiſers of thoſe that are good, caſting con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt upon thoſe Principles and Perſons which were a cheering and ſtrengthening to them in the day of their ſtreights, refuſing the one as not ſquaring to their greatneſs, and impriſoning or ſhaking hands with the other, as too ſullen or noble to be vaſſals thereto: Laſtly, lovers of pleaſures more than lovers of God, careleſs Daughters at eaſe in <hi>Zion,</hi> who are gone up to their fathers bed, and have beſtowed the ornaments the Lord put upon them, for the dreſſing up the old Harlot again, which though themſelves had been teaching before, yet fell in love with her after above meaſure, to wit, greatneſs and glory in the fleſh, while Chriſt ſtands without door as crucified and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten; ſo that they having loſt their ſavour, from them hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded ſourneſs upon the ſpirits, and filthineſs upon the actions of many others who had a ſavour before: their fall being not alone, but thereat, as it were, the heavens were removed, and the ſtarrs therein darkened; Righteouſneſs and Truth being as the Heavens over our Land, and many excellent ſpirits, as lights and ſtarrs to men, are alſo darkened and fallen together with them; this firſt departure is a ſorrow, but the other adds thereto.</p>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:48979:16"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:48979:16"/>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:48979:17"/>
               <head>Second departure from the Faith, what it is.</head>
               <p>NOt many years ſince Jeſus Chriſt began to ſhine forth in clearer principles and doctrines of light and grace, juſtification and faith, whereby the darkneſs and bondage of the Law, with the Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers thereof, paſſed away, and liberty and peace in him brake forth: ſevere deſcriptions &amp; preachings of Chriſt as a Law-giver &amp; Judge, which were as the vail upon him, gave place to more evangelical ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtations of him, as a Saviour of ſinners; the Covenant is heaven, compleatneſs in the Head began to be more opened, and the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple came to Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> as the children of the free-woman, as ſaved already in the Lord, and ſet up above all things in him.</p>
               <p>This Grace and Liberty in Chriſt being by ſome turned into wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſs and liberty in the fleſh; by very many into diſpute and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention about the letter and form, has given occaſion to the old Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to enter again into the houſe new ſwept and garniſhed, that is, the Law-working ſpirit, denying the bleſſed Attonement and Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs as already in the Head the Perſon of Chriſt, in zeal to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Attonement and Righteouſneſs by obedience to the Light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: which myſtery of iniquity works more ſecretly in the Churches, who too much preſs and praiſe a certain perfection by their rule and order, but more manifeſtly in the people called Quakers, of both whom it may be ſaid, whilſt their firſt light and love, liberty and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in Chriſt the Head was turned into ſtrife about the letter and bitings of one another by the firſt, they are in danger to be conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and deſtroyed by the laſt; a people indeed that have ſhew like a Lamb, but ſpeak like a Dragon devouring words to deſtroy both old and young, not ſparing the flock, whom nothing ſufficeth (as to me yet appears) but to tear out of our faith, knowledge and profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the bloud of attonement, redemption and reconciliation by that one Sacrifice offered once and for ever, to blot out of our hearts the name, remembrance, the light and joy thereof, till no other Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion nor liberty be known but by a pretended divinity or light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, working it in us through our perfect obedience thereunto; which his true ſenſe is to ſay, the vail is yet ſpread, the Law yet is ſtanding, the Lamb is to be ſlain, all things continue as they were from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, ye are yet in your ſins, till by obedience to the light within you be redeemed.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:48979:17"/>
               <p>The glorious Reſt and Liberty in Chriſt the Head, as it is the light of our eyes, the girdle of our loyns, to conduct and defend us from the miſts and darts, whether proceeding from the Law, Philoſophy, or Satanical myſtery; ſo if once we ſuffer our ſelves to be ſpoiled of them, our ſtrength is departed and our eyes put out, and we betraid unto every Fox out of the hole, and Boar out of the wood, unto eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry confuſion, diſtemper, or deceit which may come amongſt us; therefore ſtand faſt in the Liberty wherewith Chriſt hath made you free, that Liberty in him, which is in being as to the Spirit, when in you are felt nothing but buffetings and ſtreights as in the fleſh: thus theſe departures from the faith have been as a door ſet open, the one to let in upon us the o<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d ſpirit of tyranny upon our bodies, the ther of legality upon our ſpirits, and the darkneſs and rebuke that is upon us is very great.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Chriſt that dyed at</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>how far acknowledged and how far denied by this people to be the Redeemer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>THis leads me to two Queſtions of weightieſt conſideration as to this people.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Whether they deny the Chriſt that dyed at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to be the Redeemer?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whether they eſtabliſh a Righteouſneſs by the Law?</p>
               <p>As to the firſt, how far they affirm or deny: I ſhall give that juſt judgement, and therein do them that right I deſire they may do unto me: That Chriſt became fleſh, was made in the likeneſs of men, therein humbled himſelf, and became obedient to death, that he might become a living example to all generations of perfection, thus far they affirm and have a zeal for Chriſt: that in that body of his fleſh, through that obedience to death, he crucified our old man, purged away ſin, made reconciliation for iniquity, and perfected for ever all that are ſanctified, this they deny (as to me it appears) and the faith thereof.</p>
               <p>The Goſpel has in it morality and myſtery; the morality of it is this, that Chriſt came forth from God, a man holy and innocent, obedient in all things to the light or will of God, and left that obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience for an example unto others; this ſets forth Chriſt onely as a Law-giver, as one who came to give a Law more divine and perfect than others before him had done; and as thus he is known by this people, and ſet forth by their words and writings. The myſtery is
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:48979:18"/> this, that Chriſt the righteous, the bleſſed and Lord of the Law, was made for us ſin, a curſe and under the Law; that was we who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leive, being the unjuſt, the curſed and under the Law, are made in him the righteouſneſs of God, the bleſſed and no more under the Law.</p>
               <p>The Goſpel, as a Commandment and peice of morality, may be read and beleived by every man, and ſo was taught by the Popiſh School men, and is at this day by ſuch Miniſters as are more zealous for duty than grace; the Goſpel as a myſtery or free gift can onely be known to whom it is given, and ſo is clearly known and ſincerely and worthily preached not by many: obedience to moral Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples is the divinity of Pagans; to the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> the divinity of the Jews; to the preceptive part of the Goſpel of Jeſuites and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts; to the Light within of the ſo called Quakers; theſe indeed ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel one another as to Notion and Rule, but they agree all in one as to principle or bottom, that is, that work or obedience to ſome law or rule, is the way to redemption, perfection and God, the ſum of all is this, a Jeſus in fleſh as a Preacher of perfection, alſo as dying for an example to us they beleive and teach; the Jeſus that dyed, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in by bloud and ſpirit perfected us for ever in himſelf, they deny, they know not: whoſoever deny the bloud of attonement in the death of Chriſt, know not the Son, not the Father in him, nor the grace in his boſom, nor our glory in him; and to all ſuch in ſome bowels of compaſſion, I ſay, you may walk a while, during your hour, in the light of your fire, and warm your ſelves in the ſparks you have kindled, conceits of approaching perfection and the glory of God by a righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and croſs ſet up in your fleſh, but you ſhall not be able to ſtand before God and the Lamb in the day of his appearing, whoſe bloud, whoſe travels, whoſe ſacrifice on the Croſs is of no more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count with you?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Whether this people build up a righteouſneſs by the Law.</head>
               <p>THe other Queſtion is reſolved in this, onely for fuller ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it may be weighed by it ſelf. The Law and Prophets teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied of Chriſt, and continued till he came, who fulfilled all that was written therein, even the righteouſneſs of the Law, whereby he was juſtified according to the Law; and ſo it is ſaid, he was a Miniſter of the Curcumciſion: being made thus under the Law or firſt Teſtament, he was to ſtand or fall, to live or dye upon account of works accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:48979:18"/> to the nature and terms of that Teſtament he was under, as it is written, he that doth theſe things ſhall live by them, and therefore the reward unto Chriſt that worked was not reckoned of grace, but of debt; and ſo he was made under the Law, fulfilled the Law, and was juſtified according to the Law.</p>
               <p>That God requires the ſame obedience of us as of him, and that through offering up our ſelves in the ſame obedience he did, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come juſtified in meaſure and degree according to the meaſure of obedience; being perfectly juſtified, when come up to the ſame meaſure of obedience that Chriſt did, not before, this they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm.</p>
               <p>The concluſion is this, that even as Chriſt by doing the works of the Law was juſtified according to the Law, after the ſame manner by the ſame works done by us in the ſame ſpirit, unto the ſame meaſure we become juſtified and accepted with God, that is, by the works of the Law; the righteouſneſs of the Law ſaith thus, he that doth the will of God commanded in the Law is ſanctified thereby, and ſhall live therein; the righteouſneſs of faith ſayes, he that works not but beleives the will of God is already done by the offering of the body of Chriſt, by this will is he ſanctified and perfected for ever; of theſe they take away the ſecond, and eſtabliſh the firſt, that is, the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of the Law.</p>
               <p>God having wrought all things for us in the Perſon of Chriſt, this is our righteouſneſs, and that Truth which is firſt; God working all things in us by Chriſt is the fruit or manifeſtation of our righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and that truth which comes after; theſe when together are both Goſpel-truths, yet in their own order; when the firſt is alone with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the other, it is turned into a principle of carnal Libertiniſme; where this laſt is alone without the firſt, it is made a principle of my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Legality: both theſe Truths have their glory, but in a different reſpect, the firſt as in Chriſt the Head, onely viſible to faith, therefore to the Children of Reaſon, the law and the letter not known nor diſcerned, nor by them deſired nor praiſed; the other has its glory in the members, upon the fleſh, as therein ſeen and felt, therefore more eyes are upon it, more admirers of it, and a greater name and ſhew thereof in the world than of the other.</p>
               <p>The Myſtery of God manifeſt in fleſh was a miniſtration of infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite neceſſity as to us, that thereby all ſin might firſt be taken away, and the reconciliation made; this being done in him for all, made way moſt bleſſedly for the other myſtery of God, Chriſt in us, to be
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:48979:19"/> brought forth: I cannot, I did not know Chriſt Jeſus a fountain of living waters in me, until I firſt knew and beleived that I was waſhed, ſanctified and juſtified in him before any good done in me or by me: we love not him by bringing forth the fruits of love to him in our members, till we knew that he loved us firſt by the fruits of love ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted for us in our Head: God as having perfected me for ever in the body of Chriſt through the Spirit, appears to me with open face as love, as light, a father and freind, as nigh me, I in him, and he in me: God as having not ſaved me in himſelf already, ſo he appears with a vail upon his face, the ſight of him terrible, and to come near him is conſuming fire; can two walk together except they be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed:</p>
               <p>It is a faithful ſaying, and a ſure rule of judgement, and will ſtand for ever; that as the greateſt zeal for the ſacrifice in the body of Chriſt, excluding his ſpiritual appearance in us, is a profeſſing him as afarre off, but not a joyning or bringing us together into one; ſo the moſt ſpiritual pretences to Chriſt in us, excluding the ſacrifice for us in the body of his fleſh, is to bring God and us together before we be agreed, that is, before the propitiation for ſins or attonement be performed or done: woe unto them that profeſs they are brought nigh unto God in the death of the Mediatour, but come not unto God by him in the ſpirit of him, theſe have onely the form, but not the power of faith; woe unto them that would enter in or come nigh unto God, excluding the death of the Mediator, the Man Chriſt Jeſus, as the onely way unto him, ſuch have loſt both the form and power of faith. Darkneſs and deluſion works upon men by theſe two miſtakes; ſome preach Chriſt as the Head, but bring not men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to union with him; others preach Chriſt as doing all things in union with us, but hold not the Head as having done all for us in himſelf; theſe condemn each other, both are condemned by the children of faith, who rejoyce in Chriſt Jeſus as having overcome all things for us, as the Head over all things to us, and who wait till the ſame vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory be declared in us by his appearance in us.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Chriſt's firſt and laſt Comings what? and a Queſtion anſwered.</head>
               <p>FOr further ſatisfaction, another great Queſtion concerning this people may be taken into ſerious and humble conſideration; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may not they be that Angel of God that ſhould fly through the midſt of Heaven preaching the Goſpel of the Kingdom unto
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:48979:19"/> all Nations a little before the end ſhould come?</p>
               <p>Two things ſearched out, may give light and reſolution herein; the Comings of Chriſt firſt and ſecond, and the laſt coming of Anti-chriſt: the Comings of Chriſt and his work in both are expreſſed, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 9.26, 28. once in the end of the world hath he appeared to put away ſin by the ſacrifice of himſelf; ſo Chriſt was once offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to bear the ſins of many, and unto them that look for him the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time ſhall he appear without ſin unto ſalvation: the fleſh, ſin and death, with all the evils of mankind, were laid upon Chriſt toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who being the righteouſneſs, wiſdom and power of God could not be held of them, but as <hi>Sampſon</hi> the new ropes, ſo he rent them from off him on the Croſs, and together with his body buried them in his grave, wherein a myſtery unknown to ſenſe and reaſon, but known to faith, they lie to this day hid and covered, taken out of the ſight of God, and the conſcience of the beleiver, as perfectly as if they had never been; ſo that as the floud of <hi>Noah</hi> overwhelmed the old world, that it was not; or as the Sun ſhining at noon-day van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſheth the leaſt ſhadow of darkneſs that it is no more, ſo he that was the brightneſs of the Fathers glory, and the deep fountain of <hi>David,</hi> aboliſhed and purged away ſin by himſelf that it is no more: if ſenſe, or reaſon, or the natural conſcience may be judge in things of God, theſe things are not ſo; but let all ſuch know, that this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel of Chriſt is a myſtery hid from ſuch eyes or principles of fleſh: that Religion that ſaith ſin is not done away for us in the Head, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe felt in part in our earthly members, whatſoever honour it may take to it ſelf as above others, yet is but built upon the ſame princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples with all the falſe Religions of the world, to wit, ſenſe, reaſon and unbeleiving conſcience, that is to ſay, the Law, thus Chriſt's firſt coming was to take away ſin.</p>
               <p>As Chriſt firſt appeared bearing and taking away ſin, ſo he ſhall appear the ſecond time without ſin, that is, not as at firſt condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, bearing and taking away ſin, for th<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s he did once when he offered up himſelf: as he firſt came cloathing himſelf upon with our ſin, ſo he ſhall come again cloathing us upon with his everlaſting righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs; once he came in Grace, taking upon himſelf the ſin, the ſentence that was upon us, then he ſhall come in more grace as having taken away ſin both from off us and himſelf: his firſt coming united him to our fleſh, and us unto him, all his were gathered together in him in one body on the Croſs, his ſecond coming ſhall unite us toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with him in one glory and ſpirit, and ſhall gather all Saints into
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:48979:20"/> one in himſelf, as it is ſaid, <hi>The Lord my God ſhall come and all his Saints with thee:</hi> we who beleive are entered into Reſt, we have Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, perfection and life already, but hid in him; we wait for the ſame at his ſecond coming, not to be done over again, but to be revealed in us: thoſe that ſhall trouble them who have beleived in Jeſus, by charging them of ſin, and calling to a Redemption as a thing yet to be done, or that ſhall declare him coming again to charge or accuſe his people of ſin, to ſet up in them a croſs of attonement and redemption from ſin; ſuch do make void his firſt coming in fleſh, which was to beat away ſin; ſuch are not the Angel that ſhall publiſh his ſecond appearance, which is without ſin unto ſalvation.</p>
               <p>Jeſus Chriſt in Perſon, as raiſed up above all Principalities and Powers, is the Head of his Church; all that are Chriſt's, whether thoſe that are fallen aſleep, or that yet remain alive, are in a myſtery, raiſed up already in him, as in union with their Head; they are ſo, but they appear not ſo: as all that were Chriſt's were raiſed up to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with him when he was raiſed up, ſo they ſhall all come toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with him when he ſhall appear again, the dead out of the graves, and the living changed, and all this by vertue of union, the members with the Head: as Chriſt is not Head in Spirit alone, but as the whole Perſon; ſo his ſecond appearance will not be in Spirit alone, but alſo in Perſon; and as we are his members, not as to the Spirit alone, but alſo as to the body ſpiritual, ſo our gathering together unto the coming of the Lord will not be in Spirit onely, but alſo in the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual body: thus the coming of the Lord in his heavenly Perſon, and our meeting of him in our heavenly tabernacle or incorruptible ſtate will be together; the union of Head and Members, and the evidence of Scriptures agreeing thereto perſwading me ſo.</p>
               <p>Let this union be kept clear as to our underſtanding, and entire from firſt to laſt, ſo ſhall the diſputes of many and the diverſities of their faith about the coming of the Lord be cleared and ended, and the profeſſions of this people will appear to be not according to Truth, who ſome of them ſay, to us the Day is come and the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows are fled away; that Day being as the Lightening that ſhall ſhine from Eaſt to Weſt, that is, not coming to ſome firſt, but to all that are Chriſts together, bringing forth Redemption, not of the Spiritt alone, but alſo of the body, &amp; bringing forth our Lord Jeſus, not onely in Spirit but alſo in Perſon, and with him all that are his at coming.</p>
               <p>Wherefore our union in Chriſt the Head, and his union with us the members, are Truths of a diſtinct nature and conſideration: accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:48979:20"/> to the firſt we are in him compleat already; according to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we know him in part, and grow up in meaſures: to be in him compleat is a ſtate more inward, mor hid, ſeen onely to faith; to have him in us encreaſing and in part is a thing more in ſight, and ſeen to ſenſe and feeling: learn and beleive your ſelves perfect in him, and wait and groan for the manifeſtation thereof in your members; let no man ſpoil you of your reward in the firſt, if you would not fail and come ſhort of the laſt; live by faith alwayes in him, though the clear and comfortable ſenſe of him live not alwayes in you: thus much of Chriſt his firſt and ſecond Comings.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Anti-chriſt's laſt coming, what and how.</head>
               <p>COncerning Anti-chriſt in his laſt coming it may be ſaid; a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of carnal things with ſpiritual, Law and Reaſon with Chriſt, was the Egg of Anti chriſtianiſme, wherein that Kingdom be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan, and whereby it has been nouriſhed and continued unto this day: Circumciſion and Philoſophy under the Pagan power; Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony and works under the Papal; ſubtil ſpeculations in the dayes of the School-men; and fair ſhews in the fleſh in theſe our times; all theſe in their ſeveral ſeaſons having been coupled and mingled with the things of Chriſt, and ſtanding where they ſhould not, have made Anti-chriſt appear as a myſtery, worſhipped and wondered as the true Chriſt. In times of light, or of the Apoſtles and firſt Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, he came forth in a miniſtry of light and righteouſneſs of works, that he might diſhonour and diminiſh the righteouſneſs of Chriſt; in after ages as ſpiritual lights and truths decreaſed and declined into more carnality and darkneſs, he likewiſe took up and worked by more carnal principles; in later times as truth has begun to ſhine forth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, he alſo has transformed himſelf into an Angel of light again.</p>
               <p>Thus the way and method of Antichriſt in general has been by a ſimilitude of truth to deface the Truth, or by leſſer truths to oppoſe the greater, by p<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inciples of reaſon to oppoſe the things of faith, by the letter to oppoſe the Spirit, or by the Spirit as working all in us to oppoſe Chriſt as having wrought all for us in himſelf.</p>
               <p>That Anti-chriſt in his laſt coming will obſerve the ſame method as before, to wit, a counterfeit of truth ſeems to be expreſſed by the Lord himſelf in his ſpeech to his Diſciples concerning Antichriſt's and his own laſt coming. <hi>Math.</hi> 24.5, 26, 27. <hi>Many ſhall come in my Name, ſaying, I am Chriſt; ſome ſhall ſay he is in the deſert, ſome in
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:48979:21"/> the ſecret chambers, but my coming ſhall be as lightening ſhining from Eaſt to Weſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The laſt Truths, or Truths laſt to be revealed before the coming of the Lord will be ſuch as relate to his coming; ſpiritual whiſpers and voices from Chriſt to the Virgins, behold I come quickly; and a call of the Virgins one to another, ſaying, let us go trim our lamps, and go forth to meet him, this will be the work of the Spirit and Saints at that time: Anti-chriſt will come forth in the ſame form and language, as ſuiting with that ſeaſon, ſpeaking words not of mean and low ſtrain, but of high and ſpiritual things, I am Chriſt, or he is come; his doctrine will be of things of note and wonder, deceiving and drawing many, behold he is in the deſart, among us the lovely, deſpiſed, afflicted and caſt out, not among the wiſe, mighty and noble; behold he is in the ſecret chambers, not in the multitude, the aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, the common wayes of Religion, but among us a people ſeparate, and gathered, and called out of the world into the more inward and ſpiritual way: moreover he will come forth with power all men, all things of the earth the faith religion, ſouls and bodies of them which profeſſed the Truth, but were not of the Truth, ſhall be given into his hand, and be at his devotion; the true Chriſt with his Church ſhall be as poor, weak and inconſiderable in compariſon of him: laſtly, he will come with ſignes; the world looks for a ſign, and he will come with ſigns of light, zeal and holineſs; ſigns tokens and wonders to ſight, ſenſe and judgement of all that are not in Chriſt, ſuch as if they were the very truths, workings and comings of the Son of Man himſelf; onely the Elect, ſuch as choſe not God, but were choſen of him, ſuch as have not their life in gifts and workings in the ſpiritual vigour and activity exerciſed in themſelves, but in the root of all this, that is hid with Chriſt in God; who have their redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, their life, their religion in ſomething that is perfect without, and beyond all work in themſelves, that is in Chriſt himſelf; theſe are thoſe Elect that have that in them which ſhall keep them that they cannot be deceived: he that in that day ſhall have a name written in Heaven, that is a life compleat in Chriſt, ſhall be greater than he that ſhall ſay, Lord in thy Name have we caſt out Devils, that is, we have propheſied and gone forth in the gifts, activity and power of thy Spirit.</p>
               <p>Wherefore it may be concluded concerning this people and all other; whatſoever ſpirit or doctrine in them or any other ſhall teach
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:48979:21"/> the coming of Chriſt to make redemption or reconciliation in us, as having not fulfilled the ſame for us already in himſelf, I teſtifie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, as no other but the old Law-working Spirit under a new name and form, and therein the power of Anti-chriſt coming forth in one of his higheſt and laſt counterfeits of truth, thereby to pervert the faith, and draw away the eyes and expectations of men from the true Saviour, and his true appearance, which alſo draws near.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>An account of the hope that is in me concerning the firſt and laſt appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances of Chriſt.</head>
               <p>COncerning both whoſe appearances, that which is paſt, and that which is to come, I ſhall give a ſhort account of that faith where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I ſtand, from which I truſt neither Word nor Spirit ſhall ever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move me. That Jeſus Chriſt firſt manifeſt in fleſh came forth, not onely as an example of Perfection (as ſome ſay) nor onely as a type or figure without of things to be fulfilled in us; nor onely as a Law-giver (as others) but that in his own body on the tree, through union with the eternal Spirit, he bore away and aboliſhed our ſin and death, and fulfilled the Law and Prophets, wherein God ſo reſted and therewith was ſo well pleaſed, that he ſignified the ſame by cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the blackneſs, darkneſs, thunderings and lightenings of <hi>Sinai,</hi> in the midſt whereof he dwelt before, to paſs away, and the vail of partition between him and us to rent aſunder; beſides which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption there is none other either before or after, by Angels without, or by Spirit within, that is or ſhall be wrought as to the thing, but onely as to the manifeſtation thereof.</p>
               <p>That not by following his example, or by any work, but by faith I come to know and partake of this Redemption, which was in being before in him, but with other the heavenly things hid in God, and in time manifeſted to my faith and feeling; ſo that I began not to be redeemed or loved when I firſt beleived, but I began by faith to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold and enjoy that love and redemption which was prepared and entire for me in him, before I had done either good or evil; ſin and death being finiſhed, and my old man crucified before in him as to God with whom all things are preſent; by faith I come to know it, and do reckon with him, I am as truly crucified, buried and raiſed up according to the comprehenſiveneſs of his death and crucified Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, much more than if the ſame had been acted in and upon my own Perſon.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:48979:22"/>
               <p>That while according to my inward man or in a myſtery I am in heavenly places above Law, ſin and death, yet for the exerciſe and try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al of faith, according to ſight, or my earthly man, I often walk in the valley of the ſhadow of death, in the feeling of infirmities, buffet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and fightings in the fleſh: thus I am at once both weak and ſtrong, on earth and in heaven, a ſinner and righteous; thus I know my redemption and victory as in him compleat, while I feel the ſame redemption and victory, as in me but in part and encreaſing; if my redemption were not more than what I feel, the Goſpel were not a myſtery, nor faith would be any more than ſight, nor grace have any glory.</p>
               <p>That I look for Jeſus Chriſt to come in me more in Spirit, mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſting his death, his croſs and life in me, not thereby to make attone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for ſin, but to gather me up through daily dyings and quicken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings into the full ſight, union and profeſſion of that redemption, and grace, and glory already given me freely in him: alſo I look for the appearance of the Lord Jeſus as God and man, who ſhall enlighten the Saints with his brightneſs, and ſhall cover the earth with his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, before whom all that which is againſt him ſhall be conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by him, and that which is of him ſhall yeild up it ſelf to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected in him, as the leſſer in the greater; this is my Teſtimony and my hope.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Light, Purity and Power of this people examined what it is.</head>
               <p>AFter all that hath been ſaid, ſome may retain this perſwaſion of this people, that they are a people of light, purity and power above all others: As to their Light I would ſay; That there is a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry that knows Chriſt onely as in an Hiſtory, and teach him ſo, that preſſeth onely the outward letter according to principles of Law and natural Reaſon, but know not the myſtery and Spirit therein; what they can comprehend by the letter and reaſon, that they teach, and what is more they do judge errour, hereſie, and to their power op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and perſecute; this is a Miniſtry of darkneſs.</p>
               <p>There is a Miniſtry alſo, that teacheth Chriſt onely as an Allegory or figure of things to be done in us, the croſs and bloud without one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly typing and ſignifying the croſs, and bloud, and ſpirit within us; <hi>Moſes, John</hi> and Chriſt with their ſeveral Miniſtries being onely as tranſient forms, figures and examples of another and more ſpiritual Miniſtry within that onely makes perfect; this doctrine indeed has a
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:48979:22"/> glory with the natural man, or him that is led by the principles of Law or heightened Reaſon, but has no glory with afflicted ones, who are under workings of wrath, and ſpoiled of all, let the Maſters of ſuch doctrines with all their diſciples know, the Law was an Allego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry or ſhadow of good things in Chriſt, had nothing in it ſelf, but ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified all in another, and referred us over to him; this was but the weakneſs and emptineſs of the Law, it was but an Allegory.</p>
               <p>So they that preach the Perſon of Chriſt, and Redemption in him, to be onely an Allegory of things in us, ſuch ſet not forth Chriſt in glory but weakneſs; this is the emptineſs of Chriſt, that he was but a figure, having done nothing for us in himſelf, but onely point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us to another, the Spirit to work Redemption in us, this is a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry of darkneſs, but under a form of Light.</p>
               <p>Which ſets forth Chriſt in moſt light, let it be judged, he that ſayes Chriſt has already by himſelf done away the miniſtration of condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and death, which was as a cloud of darkneſs ſpread over us, as a thick vail before us, that we could not come unto God, and in the place thereof hath brought forth a miniſtration of righteouſneſs and life, whereby a way is opened into the holieſt, into the light and glory of God; that ſaith, <hi>Sing oh heavens, for the Lord hath done it, ſhout ye lower parts of the earth, break forth into ſinging ye mountains, oh for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt and every tree therein, for the Lord hath redeemed</hi> Jacob <hi>and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied himſelf in</hi> Iſrael; all things that were againſt us are overcome on his croſs, and deſcended into his deep grave for ever; nothing remains but that you receive this Saviour as having done all things for you, as working all things in you; or he that ſaith, Chriſt came once into the world a Teacher of Perfection, and a living Example therein; but is now come in us, ſetting up a Law of condemnation and death, wherein if we abide, and bear the indignation of God and puniſhment of ſins, in his Spirit and after his example; through theſe ſufferings as by the bloud of the Croſs ſhall the Attonement and redemption be made and perfected, if we be perfect in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; and that we are not to beleive any ſuch thing that the bloud of Chriſt without takes away ſins; ſin is not taken away, nor redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made till the ſame obedience and ſufferings be fulfilled in us as in him: this doctrine becauſe pointing to the bloud, the Croſs, the Redeemer within may by ſhaken and darkened hearts be called a doctrine of light, but indeed it bringeth back the ſhadows and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of the Law again, remembrance of ſin, ſuffering, ſacrifice, wrath; and ſo far from being a Light, that it ſhuts up the light, grace
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:48979:23"/> and glory of God, that he cannot be ſeen any other wayes than through a vail far thicker than that of <hi>Moſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Chriſt as appearing above all mountains, as Head over all Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palities and Powers to his Church, ſo he is a Light; as by the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his glory he has vanquiſhed that darkneſs and death brought in by ſin, ſo he is a light; as he has in himſelf the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed all that which came in by the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> ſo he is a light, he that brings not this doctrine makes Chriſt no more a Light, but either a figure and example without, or at the beſt a Law-giver, a <hi>Moſes</hi> and an Exact or within.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Their Purity and Power examined, what it is.</head>
               <p>THere is a Purity that is ſo with men, but not before God; Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſaith Man's nature is defiled by ſin, and muſt be waſhed by our obedience; diſobedience to God was the defilement, and by obedience and mortification we return to Purity; but faith ſayes, Purity before God is the conſcience purged by the dead body of Chriſt, and the heart purified by the Spirit of faith, beleiving the ſame: who are moſt for ſpiritual Purity, they that beleive ſin already done away in him that came by bloud, water and ſpirit, and by union with him are therein waſhed and made clean every whit; or they who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend ſin not yet done away, take away our righteouſneſs in the Head ſo pure and perfect, and affirm our righteouſneſs to be but in part till perfection in obedience? if bodily exerciſe or purifying the fleſh may be called purity, divers Monks and Jeſuites eſpecially of old may claim a name herein, who yet knew little of Purity by the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of God: when almes, bodily chaſtiſements, retirement in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to holy houſes, and going on pilgrimage was beleived as the way to be perfect, no wonder if this Religion abounded; ſo where this Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple is received in power, that obedience to the light within, and all the ſeveral acts of that obedience till come unto perfection are the onely Redemption and way to be perfect; to ſee zeal and exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, labours and ſufferings, denying the pleaſures, faſhions and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms of the world in ſuch, tis not to be wondered at: to purifie the earthly members by the ſpirit is good, while the inward Man abides as in a more excellent way purified in the Head; but to purifie the members, as reckoning it our redemption, our righteouſneſs, all ſuch Purity is ſin, blindneſs and Idolatry,</p>
               <p>Laſtly, as to their Power; the Law is mighty to kill, becauſe of ſin, weak to ſave, becauſe of the fleſh; he that takes out of our ſight our righteouſneſs as in heaven, in the Lord already prepared, brings us
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:48979:23"/> back into weakneſs and bondage again, and leaves us without light or ſtrength to withſtand in the hour of temptation that may come ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by ſpirits from without, or our fleſh from within: that doctrine that declares our liberty, victory &amp; triumph to be already in being in Chriſt the Head, that ſhews us a life given unto us above all ſpiritual actings, exerciſes and comforts felt in our ſelves, a life, liberty and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection hid in Chriſt, this doctrine brings power and a ſpirit of power,</p>
               <p>Compleatneſs in the Head without Law or work, being beleived and learned, gives a ſpirit of judgement over all ſpirits and doctrines, intereſt and kinds of life, and a ſtrength of righteouſneſs which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves from the evils of all: whilſt this Truth lay hid, the Church was in bondage unto the elements of the world, will-worſhip and monkiſh holineſs having over-ſpread all; inſtability and unfaithfulneſs to this Truth does at this day deliver up many unto principles and practiſes not according to Chriſt: thus where righteouſneſs in the Head with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out work is denied, there is neither light, purity nor power, though a ſhew of all: ſpeech, or words and outward appearance was one thing, and power another with him that ſaid, I will know not the ſpeech of them that are puffed up, but their power.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Oppoſition and perſecution that is raiſed againſt this people, what to be thought of it.</head>
               <p>HAving given this general view of this people and their way, I ſhall conclude with a word concerning the oppoſition and perſecution that is every where practiſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and my ſenſe thereupon. The oppoſition made againſt that or any way that pretends to be of God, may be ſaid to proceed either from ignorance, or enmity, or truth. As to the firſt, they that have not the Spirit of light in themſelves oppoſe the ſame and the very appearance of the ſame in others; the Religion and faith of the greateſt part of the Nation is no more but traditions of others, or inventions of their own rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; the teachings of God through the Son and Spirit being things they know nothing of, and therefore the more lively, inward and ſpiritual manifeſtations of Truth they oppoſe: being in darkneſs themſelves they know not the light nor the workings of it in others, and therefore think no man ſees more than themſelves, and ſo meaſure all things by themſelves, by this ſort of men is this way every where ſpoken againſt, becauſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſhews of light and ſpirit it teſtifies againſt them as in darkneſs and the fleſh: as to this, I teſtifie againſt the Nation as fighters againſt God, while they ignorantly oppoſe any ſpirit or way, whether it be of God, or do but appear to be o<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt and the light of him is an offence to this world, therefore is his way ſuch an offence, becauſe having ſome reſemblance of him, though to me no more; what is done againſt them, though it be not done againſt him, yet is done as againſt him, and the Nations ſin is not the leſs.</p>
               <p>Others have had a taft of Light and Truth, and begun in the Spirit, but are returned back to the fleſh, and are ſit down at eaſe in their forms and intereſts; and having loſt their ſimplicity, ſavour and love to the intereſts of Light and Truth, the Goſpel and Kingdom of Chriſt; further meaſures and manifeſtations of Chriſt and Light and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:48979:24"/> of obedience thereto are as much an offence to them, as the leaſt meaſures thereof are to the other: ſtinted forms of words and worſhip were the intereſt of the Biſhops; ſtint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed meaſures of light and profeſſion are the intereſt of theſe; thoſe were at warr with every thing that was beſide their form, becauſe againſt their intereſt; theſe are at warr with what is beſide their meaſure, becauſe againſt their intereſt, while the tyranny of Princes and idolatry of Religions was heavy upon them, that Righteouſneſs and Light was ſweet that redeemed and led them out: Liberty and pleaſures in the fleſh having ſince flattered them into the policies principles and cuſtomes of the world, they take up the ſame weapons againſt encreaſes of light and reformation in others, which their op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſors took up againſt the beginnings of it in themſelves; by this ſort are this people and others oppoſed and perſecured, becauſe pretending to higher meaſures of light and righteouſneſs than they can bear, unto ſuch I ſay, it is a ſhame and ſadneſs in ſuch a day as this, that for meer differences and offences about ſpiritual things, where no more oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion is given men ſhould be delivered up unto bonds, priſons and unreaſonable men: let them live under you in peace, who break not your peace: let the true Jeſus and the true Goſpel-ſpirit ſhine forth more in our hearts and wayes, and there will not need the arm of fleſh either againſt the Whore or the Beaſt, ſpiritual or outward enemies.</p>
               <p>Truth as it is in Jeſus is the onely principle whereby to oppoſe errour, unto which Truth I do here bear witneſs, and have ſo far herein appeared againſt this people, as they have to me appeared againſt the truth in Chriſt: diſputes and ſtrifes among brethren divided in the letter, where the ſpirit is one, I avoid and forbear: Enmity and oppoſition againſt ſpiritual enlightenings in others has been the ſin of many in this Nation; if I had been left to my own heart, I ſhould have been as they; but a ſearching for more light, and a readineſs to receive it has been my frame, having through grace learned, that one beam of true Goſpel-light is more worth than the reading of many books, more mighty than all the Kingdoms of the world with all their policy, force and greatneſs. The difference between me and this people is (as I judge) no other but what is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them and Chriſt, not about words, or poſtures, or glits, or operations, but about the bloud, the attonement, the perſon of Jeſus Chriſt; if after divers conferences, read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and hearings their words and writings, I could have found the difference no more than in gifts and meaſures of light and knowledge; if I could have found them hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Head, the Perſon of the Mediatour and compleatneſs in him by faith, I ſhould have been ſilent and ſtudied unity with them.</p>
               <p>God indeed is Love, but Chriſt coming forth as righteouſneſs and peace was the manifeſtation of this Love, in him is our victory, liberty and ſongs; this Truth ſenſe feels not, reaſon cannot reach, law vails it, fleſh and bloud reſiſt it, ſpiritual wickedneſſes in all falſe Religions fight againſt it; if our faith and ſight hereof be taken from us, we are delivered up to the power of ſome of theſe earthly, dark and worldly principles; as this truth is darkened or denyed by this people, I have appeared for it: it has been my light herein by which I have written; as it is opened or ſhut upon my heart, I did here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in go or ſtand ſtill; if it had pleaſed the Lord to have encreaſed my light and faith here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, I might have written with more evidence and power; that little ſtrength that has been lent I have not denied, not knowing what uſe it may be of.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:48979:24"/>
            <head>An account of the Faith of this people in the ſeverall parts and principles thereof being made publique by a chiefe Leader of that way, <hi>J. Naylor,</hi> in his Book called <hi>Love to the Loſt;</hi> I ſhall gather up every principle by it ſelf into a ſhort and juſt ſumme; and therewith the principles of truth, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Prophets and Apoſtles, whereby we may come to an underſtanding both of their faith and the truth, and to a right judgement of their agreement or difference there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with; in doing of which I truſt the Lord of light and truth ſhall ſo command me, that I ſhall preſent this faith to others, as their own writings preſent it to me; and alſo ſet out the faith of Chriſt no otherwiſe then as it is in him.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the fall of man.</head>
               <p>THe ſumme of things ſpoken by him is, that Gods own wiſdom and power or Spirit was placed in man, whereby he had power to be the Sonne of God, and Ruler over all the creatures; this was the ſtate of the firſt man; that mans departing out of Gods own wiſdom and power or ſpirit put into him, and joyning to another, the diſobedience entred in; Gods own wiſdom and ſpirit remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning yet in him, but as a Captive; this was his fall: that by looking and turning not to any thing without, but to that of God lying under and covered within him, the ſame makes attonement in him, and reconciles unto God through his yielding up himſelfe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, which is the blood of the Croſſe; this is his Redemption.</p>
               <p>The account of truth is, that the firſt man <hi>Adam</hi> was made a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſoul, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. had a beam of light, &amp; power, &amp; glory of God, as to that appearance of him to the firſt creation, yet ſtill but a living ſoul, not a quickning ſpirit: as to his outward part, earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, not heavenly, created of earth, and feeding upon things created: as to his inward, naturall not ſpirituall; that is, having in him the perfection and beauty of a created wiſdom and power, not the eternall wiſdom and power; a candle of light, not the Sunne or fountain of light it ſelf: by that in him he ſaw the Godhead as Light, righteouſneſs, and power, but as giving a law, and a ſentence of death; thus God appeared and appeares to the firſt creation; he
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:48979:25"/> ſaw him not as his light, righteouſneſs, and power, by himſelf ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling the law, and aboliſhing death: this appearance as then lay hid in God, reſerved to be brought forth in the ſecond creation; thus was man in his firſt eſtate.</p>
               <p>That by one mans diſobedience many were made ſinners; <hi>Adam</hi> was ſo one, that he was many in one; as the root before the bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches is one, yet many as a root: departing from the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and therein from God, he diſobeyed and died, yet not as alone, but we all in his loynes: the root being unholy, ſo were the branches; all fleſh was defiled in him that was the father of all fleſh; his ſinne and death like a flood having overflown himſelf and all the earth with a curſe. This was his fall, and all ours in him.</p>
               <p>That by the obedience of one ſhall many be made righteous: Chriſt was One, as to perſon, yet many in One in a myſterie: ſo his obedience was not the righteouſneſſe of one, but of all in him: not by looking back and returning to the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> made a living ſoule, or the glory of the Godhead ſhining forth upon him; but by looking out of every thing in man to the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> made a quickning ſpirit, and the grace of God ſhining forth in him through the blood of his croſſe, we are redeemed, and that not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the righteouſneſs of the firſt, but of the ſecond <hi>Adam:</hi> thus Chriſt crucified was that wiſdom hid in God before the world un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our glory, not known by the naturall or firſt man, neither be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore nor after his fall: if there be that in the naturall man, which being turned into and followed can redeem and make atonement for him (as this man ſayes) then the blood of Chriſt is of no more effect; but do this and live.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Light and Life.</head>
               <p>He ſaith, that the light ſhining in every man is Chriſt the true light and life of men. That the going out of this Light is the cauſe of all falſe Religions, Sects, and errors; that redemption out of all theſe, out of ſinne and death is by the Light within all men as minded and obeyed; that a righteouſneſſe done as far as <hi>India,</hi> and preached as far as <hi>Corinth,</hi> where the ſame is not done in us, is the profeſſion of Phariſees, hypocrites.</p>
               <p>Faith ſaies, that God manifeſt in the fleſh, and his glory ſhining forth in the man Jeſus, vanquiſhing and doing away the miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:48979:25"/> of the law, ſin, and death for us by his own righteouſneſs and life, as excelling in glory, this is the Chriſt and light of men: the word made fleſh as the Mediatour, having purged away our ſins by himſelf, ſo he is light unto us, the ſame word as the ſpirit of reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation in us, ſo he is light within us, ſo he is not light in every man.</p>
               <p>That where faith in the blood of the Mediator is not, there is darkneſs the mother of Errors, and all falſe Religions; every of which are more or leſs bottomed upon the Law in the Conſcience that is the light within, righteouſneſs by obedience or work be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Root of all, they only differ in the Rule; ſome are for <hi>Moſes,</hi> others for the Alchoran, others for Holy Church, theſe for the Light within. That the righteouſneſs done in <hi>India,</hi> and Preached at <hi>Corinth</hi> is the light that ſcatters the Redemption, that leads out of all erring Religions, from ſin and death, and that the Righteouſneſs as far as <hi>India</hi> (a term of diſhonour by them put upon it) is to the true ſpiritual believer not confined in the Land of <hi>India,</hi> but according to the Divine Perſon in whom it is, is extended unto and upon all that believe, as a garment ſpread upon them for the covering of ſins, a fountain of life within them for the waſhing away ſin.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Righteouſneſs.</head>
               <p>The ſum of their faith is, that the imputed righteouſneſs that juſtifies is the Light within, or that of God in every man, which is the free gift that Saints are juſtified with this righteouſneſs by obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to it; ſo much we work or obey, ſo much juſtified and no further. That the righteouſneſs that is made a covering for ſin is an invention of men, and will not ſtand in the laſt day. Nothing ſaid of Chriſt manifeſt in fleſh, or his crucified body and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs that way.</p>
               <p>The Goſpel-faith ſaid, that the Righteouſneſs that juſtifies is Chriſt not as God alone, nor as Man alone, but as God-man in one, who being made ſin for us, did moſt graciouſly and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly upon the Croſs aboliſh and overwhelm ſin, condemnation and the Curſe laid upon his fleſh, by that Omnipotent righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, life and bleſſing that was in his God head.</p>
               <p>That not by the works of God in us, but by the work of God in Chriſt, with the brightneſs of his glory purging away our ſin in
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:48979:26"/> himſelf are we juſtified without works, only through faith: Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption is a work wholly and entirely in the Perſon of Chriſt as Head, revealed and given unto us through faith, and confeſſed and manifeſted by works: by once offering of his body he hath perfected for ever all that are his; he that truly believes this is perfectly purged, and there is no more Conſcience of ſin though yet the feeling of ſin; by this faith is the creature made perfect in righteouſneſs at once as in Chriſt, by the Light within he is not made perfect till obedience be perfected; judge whither Doctrine leads to perfection.</p>
               <p>That the righteouſneſs of Chriſt as a covering upon ſin preſenting the believer in him as righteous to God, while ungodly and in ſins, as to his own ſenſe, is a myſtery of God that never entered into the heart or invention of man: but that righteouſneſs that covers us no further then our works, is the invention of man's reaſon, the very life and ſoul of all falſe Religions: the firſt is <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, bringing forth her children unto liberty, joy and reſt, as compleat in the Lord; the laſt is <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> beneath, bringing forth to bondage, and hanging down the Head, labouring for a perfection in the fleſh, not diſcerning that already in the Lord. Was the woman that touched but the hem of Chriſt's gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment made as whole as they whom he touched with his hand? were the Diſciples that ſat at Jeſus his feet made clean every whit, as he that leaned in his boſome? or was as the Child while under Tutors and Governours yet heir of all things? and is it not ſo now? doth God meaſure out his love and everlaſting righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs by inches and ells according to our obedience as men in a bargain? what grace or glory is in ſuch a faith? where ſuch a Goſpel is received, judge what is their ſpirit; unmerciful, cenſori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. Let theſe people know, that the righteouſneſs as in the Lord though now leaſt in fight ſhall be a ſhadow, a Cover, a Cloud upon Saints under which they ſhall be ſafe, where righteouſneſs as only within, or the Light within where the blood is not, though now having a glory with Religious Reaſon and unſtable ſouls, ſhall be condemned as found wanting: let Saints ſtand faſt in their Liberty in Chriſt, while infirmity is in themſelves, yet let them look for the Revelation of it in themſelves, if it may be to ſwallow up all infirmity; let ſuch as boaſt of their Liberty in the Lord, and deſire not to be gathered into it in their members, know, they have neither liberty in him nor in themſelves.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:48979:26"/>
               <head>Concerning the Word.</head>
               <p>They ſay, That the Light within all men is the word of God, ſufficient in it ſelf without any other word for Counſel and ſtrength: that this word or light in all men is that of which the Scriptures were given to declare, and can be underſtood only by it, That this Light or word be obeyed, waſheth, cleanſeth, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formeth man to God, and this is the Reconciliation. The inference. If the light within every man be the word, the Goſpel, then all Ages have had, all Nations have had the Goſpel in equality of Light and fulneſs, if they would obey it; then <hi>Moſes,</hi> Prophets and Chriſt were all but as one in Authority and Miniſtery; equal and one, that is, teſtifying and pointing to the light within men, not to the ſon of <hi>David,</hi> the Mediator, him that came as none before him, nor after ſhall, by Spirit, Water, and Blood.</p>
               <p>Truth ſaies, that the light within every man, is the remaining ſparkle of that Law or light that God ſet up in greater glory in the firſt or natural man, and ſerves in all Nations as the Candle of the Lord, repreſenting God only as under a vail, that is, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Law, and by things that are made.</p>
               <p>That Chriſt come in the fleſh, in himſelf fulfilled the voices of the Law and Prophets, and put an end to their Miniſtery, as being the Miniſter by whom God would ſpeak in the laſt times; this is the Word, the Oracles, Figure, and Tables, with all the divers manners of God's ſpeaking under the Law, being all to ſerve but for a ſeaſon, and to be ſilent when he came who was the Living Word. Chriſt is the Word according to a twofold Miniſtery; as without us in fleſh, dying for our ſins, and riſing for our ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, ſo he was the Miniſter or Living Word of reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; as within his in ſpirit, ſo he is the inward Word or Spirit of Revelation; theſe two Miniſtries are not one without the other, both are needful for us, yet each in their order; Chriſt's Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry in fleſh muſt firſt make way for his Miniſtry in Spirit; till the Word of reconciliation had finiſhed his work of redeeming us to God by his blood, the ſpirit of revelation could not come; as it is ſaid, the Spirit was not given becauſe that Jeſus was not glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified; if no redemption by his blood in that Miniſtry without, then no Revelation of the Spirit of grace within; this people be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve not the firſt, therefore they have not the laſt; but I entreat
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:48979:27"/> them to hear, that the blood, the Croſs, the grace, the crucified body of the man Chriſt was and is to the true believer as the loud voice of God, ſpeaking reconciliation and redemption to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready finiſhed in himſelf, not to be done in us; as it is written, when he had ſaid it is finiſhed, he gave up the ghoſt; by that Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry without in fleſh he brought us unto God, by that Miniſtry of his ſpirit he reveals God in us; this Chriſt is the Word as in both theſe Myſteries, and one is not without the other, but the Light within every man knows him in neither; therefore together with the Law with which it is one, ought to give place.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Worſhip.</head>
               <p>He affirms, that the ſpirit of life from God, wherein is the mind, will, and love of God, the Name, power, and wiſedom of Chriſt, wherewith alone God can be acceptably worſhipped is in every man; that the way whereby the movings of this ſpirit of life and leadings may be ſeen and attained, is the Light within every man, and waiting therein; that the light or ſpirit within every man is the pattern of true worſhip; they who abide and ſerve God therein, deny all the worſhip and Religions of the world, and are well pleaſing to the Father; they who go out of this light into the letter or any thing without, go into the dead works and worſhips, darkneſs and Idolatry.</p>
               <p>The word of faith ſaies, that the law without or ſpirit in every man that ſaies do this and live, are the vail, and do keep them that are under it in the firſt Tabernable, that is waſhings, righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, redemption by obedience in us; that Chriſt's dead body was the rending of the vail or firſt Tabernacle and the way into the holieſt, through which we draw nigh unto God by the faith alone of Chriſt crucified for us, without works; to abide in any law or light whatſoever either from within or without, and to be exerciſed therein, as to be redeemed or perfected thereby, this is to worſhip God according to the Law, and as in the fleſh; but to worſhip God as already redeemed from the Law, fleſh, and ſin, as already freed and ſet up through faith in the life, ſpirit, and righteouſneſs of Chriſt; this is to worſhip the father as in ſpirit and <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>h.</p>
               <p>Th<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> the way to attain to this ſpirit of Chriſt is not by the <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the Law, or waiting in the light within every man,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:48979:27"/> which is all one, but by the hearing of faith, or Chriſt revealed in the ſoul as the end of all Laws, curſes and evils, and the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of all good things unto us; that principle placed in all men may lead unto a ſpirit of fear, zeal and activity for God in the Contemplations of him as a pure and holy God; but 'tis a far other principle, that is, Chriſt crucified for us, and the faith of him that leads unto that ſpirit of peace, power, and joy, in the beholding of God as our father in him; ſo then that ſpirit that ſhews the commandment, and leads to the ſervices thereof to be redeemed thereby, is a ſpirit which all men may attain unto; but that ſpirit that reveals the things freely given of God without Law or ſervice, is that ſpirit that is not given unto all; nor eye, nor ear, nor heart of man can ſee or find this out; he only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcends and blows where he lifts; neither being received can he be retained any longer then he pleaſeth, no more then we can reſtrain the breath in our noſtrils; that ſpirit exerciſeth the ſervants there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of with labour and hard bondage and then kills them, as prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the commandment of the Old before the blood of the New and everlaſting Teſtament; this makes his Children free and ſaves for ever, as rejoycing in the Head, and having no confidence in the fleſh or the works done therein.</p>
               <p>That the pattern of true worſhip is Jeſus Chriſt as the Oracle ſpeaking from Heaven, and the Goſpel as the Preacher on earth; the one being the ſubſtance of Heavenly things themſelves, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but the Copy; that doctrine or ſpirit whatſoever it may ſeem, that calls you to the light in every man and to that alone as the only pattern of faith and worſhip, doth but build up a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip upon the ſame foundations with the worſhips of the world, that is, righteouſneſs by the Law, and ſerves to no other end then to blot out the true attonement, the blood and water, that fountain of healing in the Perſon of Chriſt, with the very name and remembrance thereof, to bring forth inſtead thereof another attonement to be made in our perſons, which in true ſenſe is no other but the righteouſneſs of the Law.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Error, Hereſie, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>He ſaith, that the light within every man is that Spirit of truth which judgeth all deceit, but can be deceived by none that to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide or go out from this Spirit or light is errour, and the mother of all falſe worſhip, and Religions.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:48979:28"/>
               <p>It has been before proved, that the light within all men is the candle of the Lord in every naturall man revealing the law and the offences againſt that law; but the Spirit that reveales the gift of grace by one man Jeſus Chriſt the naturall man neither knows nor can receive.</p>
               <p>There are three that bear record in heaven, and they are one; there are three that bear witneſs on earth, and they agree in one; God ſending forth his Son in our fleſh for a propitiation for ſins, this is the witneſs of the Father, as the fountain of grace and truth; Chriſt comming forth as the Image and brightneſſe of the Father, purging away our ſins by himſelf, and returning to God, this is the witneſs of the Son, as the fulneſs of grace and truth; the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Chriſt coming into our hearts, revealing the righteouſneſs of Chriſt and the life of Chriſt in us, this is the witneſs of the Spirit.</p>
               <p>Now among theſe witneſſes there is ſuch an Unity, that he that denies one, denies all; the witneſſes are one and their teſtimony one, yet each in their order; the Father ſpoke, and appeared, and bowed himſelf to ſinners, but ſo as in the Mediator the man Chriſt; the Son redeemed ſinners, but ſo as he did in his own body, not in ours; the ſpirit comes unto ſuch, but ſo as he leads them into the Light and fulneſs of Chriſt, not the light in every man; to divide from any of theſe, or to ſet one againſt another is Error; Jews and Turks believe in God, but not as in the Son; they divide from the Son, and ſo have not the Father; the litteral and carnal Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors after a ſort believe in God as in the Mediator, but deny his ſpirit in their hearts; theſe divide from the ſpirit, and ſo have neither the Son nor the Father; this people believe in God as by the Light within men redeeming from ſin, but not as in the Man Jeſus having done it already; and ſo deny the witneſs of the Son, and have neither Son nor Father.</p>
               <p>Chriſt is the band of unity between God and men; in him Mercy, and Truth, righteouſneſs and peace do kiſs each other; in him, God and ſinners are met together, reconciled, and at unity; in him God comes down to ſinners; by him we come unto God; in him the bleſſed Divinity, and the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> that is the humane nature are in covenant, in union; the Covenant, the union was made by the Croſs, by blood, by the body of Chriſt, this was the Sons witneſſe; take heed, he that divides you from the Son and this his witneſſe, ſets you at ſuch a difference
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:48979:28"/> with the Majeſty of God, as no light nor ſpirit within you can attone or make up; thus Error is not to divide from the Light within all men, but from Chriſt the Head, the fulneſs of all Truth, in whom we only ſee and have the Father and Spirit, and without whom all Religions are fleſhly or myſtical Idolatries.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Faith.</head>
               <p>He ſaies, the meaſure or light of God in every man is Gods righteouſneſs, perfection; that turning into this righteouſneſs and adiding therein, is the receiving of the righteouſneſs of Chriſt by faith; that by waiting in the light within through faith and obedience thereto righteouſneſs is wrought in, and unrighteouſneſs wrought out; and ſo the creature is made free from ſin, not a word of the Faith in the perſon of Chriſt, or the operation of God in him for us.</p>
               <p>The ſcope of their Doctrine herein, and in all the height and depth of it, ſeems plainly this, that a meaſure of the eternal Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity is in every man, by turning whereinto, out of all ſayings, writings, perſons, operations, Scriptures, or Chriſt without, the ſame doth through obedience thereto deſtroy and purge away ſins out of us, and ſo redeems and reconciles unto God.</p>
               <p>The precious faith ſaies, that the eternal word manifeſt in fleſh, being the ſubſtantial fulneſs of the Divine life and righteouſneſs, and having thereby vanquiſhed in his fleſh, and buried in his grave our ſins and death with all powers viſible or inviſible that were againſt us, this is he who is the pure, perfect, and acceptable righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of God.</p>
               <p>That to look away from all the voices and condemnations of the Law without, or conſcience within, from all things in our fleſh and heart, whither good or evil, unto the perſon of Jeſus Chriſt himſelf; and to believe him to be our righteouſneſs, ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and liberty, as in the hidden myſterie of faith; which to our ſenſe or earthly members we are in infirmities, buffetings, and bondage; this is to receive the righteouſneſs of Chriſt by faith; the faith of things not ſeen to ſenſe and reaſon, yet hid in God.</p>
               <p>That by him all that believe are juſtified from all things by the Law of the ſpirit according to the Conſcience, from which they could not be juſtified by the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> without, or the work of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:48979:29"/> the Law written within according to the fleſh; by the eternal ſpirit in the blood of Jeſus were ſins waſhed away in the perſon of Chriſt before either faith or work; by faith the ſame is brought to light in the Conſcience, by the works of faith is manifeſt in the body; as I am in the fleſh I labour between light and darkneſs, fleſh and ſpirit, in fightings, in work; as I am in Chriſt, I am entered into reſt and victory, and know no more work but Chriſt to be all; that faith that cannot ſee juſtification in Chriſt till full mortification in the fleſh, will be found to be that fleſhly Reaſon that cannot enter within the vail, that is, beyond the Law, ſenſe, and reaſon.</p>
               <p>Let theſe things be weighed, that the purging away ſin by a meaſure of God or light within, is a baptiſm deviſed by reaſon, and may waſh away the filth of the fleſh before men, and hath a glory in appearance; but the anſwer of a good Conſcience in the death and reſurrection of the man Jeſus, will be found to be the Baptiſm that ſaves before God, and brings forth the true glory within.</p>
               <p>That this people ſeeking after righteouſneſs by perfect obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the light within, and the Jews ſeeking it by obedience to the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> without, are both in one ſpirit and under one law of work; and differ no more but in the Copies of the Law; thoſe ſay, the Law in the Conſcience is holy, juſt, and pure, and by obedience thereunto the unholineſs and ſin is taken away; theſe ſay the Law upon Tables of ſtone is holy, juſt, and ſpiritual, and by obedience to it they think to attain righteouſneſs; let both theſe know, that neither the letter of the Law without, nor the light of the Law within, how holy and pure ſoever, but Chriſt Jeſus crucified as the end of both, and faith in him is that which ſhall preſerve men blameleſs and without ſpot before him at his coming; all other coverings, whither by Law, letter, or light within, if without that in him, ſhall be too ſhort in that day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Hope.</head>
               <p>He ſaith, to hope that that of God in every man or a Chriſt may be revealed to take away ſin; to give freedome from ſin in this life, is the pure, the reaſonable hope that makes not aſhamed; that to hope ſalvation while the witneſe in the Conſcience con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns of ſin, is the Divels hope, and the unreaſonable hope; that
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:48979:29"/> they who have this hope, look only for ſpirit, light, word, and righteouſneſs without, and deny the witneſs within, and Chriſt within the hope of glory.</p>
               <p>To believe Chriſt hath already once in the end of the world appeared to put away ſin by the ſacrifice of himſelf, whereby we are ſaved through faith according to the inward man, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.26. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.5 and to look and long for him to appear again with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſin unto ſalvation and redemption of the body or outward man; this is the lively hope that makes not aſhamed, that gives perfection and ſtrength in him, while yet poor and wanting in our ſelves.</p>
               <p>That to reſt in hope that I am ſaved already from ſin and wrath in Chriſt the Head through his blood and ſpirit, whiles conſcience condemns of ſin in my fleſh; this is the hope againſt hope, the hope of grace and faith, againſt the hope of Law and conſcience, or ſenſe and feeling; this is the hope unreaſonable indeed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Law, and natural light; but moſt true and reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, according to an higher Law and reaſon in God, that is, the Word made fleſh, and made ſin for us; this hope in many is no more but an imagination or idle notion, living in the pleaſures of ſin; in ſuch it was begotten by the letter or Reaſon, or at the beſt by a vaniſhing flaſh of Light; but where it is begotten by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habiting and abiding ſpirit, there it is a hope beholding the glory of the Lord, and changing the creature into the ſame image in the Lord; the hope that ſees the love of the father ſhed forth upon us in the blood of attonement, and all ſins and evils finiſhed therein, is the hope that gives reſt to the afflicted, wearied, and not comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and lifts up the head above the floods of all waters that can come againſt them.</p>
               <p>He that truly looks unto the righteouſneſs and grace in the perſon of the Mediator, doth alſo wait in hope for the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, light and ſpirit of the Mediator to be revealed within him; therfore his words are a ſlander; to know Chriſt only as without, &amp; to know him only as within are both a like Error; to conclude, they that are Chriſts are ſaved already, but it is by hope, not in clear and full enjoyment; the hope is laid up in him, but not ſeen to ſenſe and feeling; what a man ſees or enjoys, why doth he yet hope for it?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:48979:30"/>
               <head>Concerning Love.</head>
               <p>His Doctrine is, that Gods love to the world in ſending his Son is this, that God had given a light in every man to condemn ſin in the fleſh, and take it away through walking after the ſpirit, and denying the works of the fleſh; that God's love in the creature, doth likewiſe condemn all ſin in others, not flattering or ſparing any, and then covers them with righteouſneſs.</p>
               <p>Was this Gods great and abounding love in ſending his Son? is it no more but God giving a light in all men condemning of ſin, and taking it away in them? or was it not rather herein, that when the Law was weak, the fleſh weak, while we were yet ſinners and in our blood, while there was no man, no Interceſſor, that even then God ſent his Son a propitiation for ſins: who came down unto us not in the nature of Angels, but in our fleſh, and therein through death quenched in the ſtill deep waters of his meekneſs and love, the anger, enmity, ſin and death, with all things that might ſeparate us from the love of God; which of theſe was the great love? let the Scriptures, ſpirit, and ſpiritual man be judge; or is this God's love in men to condemn, curſe, and judge others as not juſtified and ſaved in Chriſt, whileſt they feel ſin in the fleſh? to take away my liberty, joy, and peace, which I have in Chriſt, witneſſed by the ſpirit to faith, until the ſame be witneſſed in my fleſh to ſenſe; is this divine love? to trouble them that have believed in Jeſus, the afflicted and wounded and weary, by calling them unto the miniſtration of <hi>Moſes,</hi> the fire and the ſword, the ſuffering, the indignation for ſin, and unto perfect obedience, all this as the way to redemption and righteouſneſs by Chriſt, is this the love that is of God, the grace, the meekneſs of the Goſpel? or rather is it not the love of the falſe Apoſtles, calling them to the fulfilling of the Law, that were at liberty in Chriſt? who indeed zealouſly affected, but not well, that is, that they might glory in their fleſh.</p>
               <p>God's love to his people ſpeaks woe and wrath indeed, but to the wiſe and ſtrong who will not bow to the weakneſs and fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of a crucified Chriſt, to be ſaved in him; but to the hungry and weary, to the leaſt of the little children that are in Chriſt, it ſpeaks peace; fear not, your ſins are forgiven you for his names ſake; wherefore to bring forth a full Chriſt, a fulneſs of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:48979:30"/> life and liberty in Chriſt to a creature empty and deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of any ſuch thing, this is that love that feeds the hungry, cloathes the naked, and gives water in the wilderneſs; there is a generation that flatters, and ſpares in ſin them whom the Lord condemns; this is to juſtifie the wicked; there is another generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that charges and reproves of ſin whom the Lord hath juſtified; let this people fear that this is their error; both are alike abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination to the Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Judgement.</head>
               <p>His words ſummed up are, That the light in every man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning of ſin is the miniſtration of judgement and condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and as it is received is light and ſalvation, redeeming from all uncleaneſs; that the ſpirit of judgement that went forth in the Prophets againſt all unrighteouſneſs, is come forth in a people now; I underſtand, in him and in them.</p>
               <p>The faith of the Goſpel ſaith, that Chriſt having all judgement committed to him; in the body of his fleſh, judged and gave up to condemnation and death, the prince of this world, the fleſh, the glory of man, his ſin and righteouſneſs, and having done all, he went to the father and was ſeen no more; he being the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Gods own righteouſneſs, and being to be made righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to men, he judged and put an end to all other righteouſneſs, even to that which had a glory, as having no glory; ſo that it may be ſaid by him, that is, in his Croſs fell all the mighty Lords and Tyrants of the world, Law, ſin, and death, all which are judged and overcome by that righteouſneſs and ſpirit of life in him; by this judgement are ſinners redeemed already as in him the head.</p>
               <p>That as Chriſt hath in every Age come forth more or leſs, ſo in this laſt time he will come forth the righteouſneſs and ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his people, whoſe appearance doth and will judge the works of the Law as well as the luſts of the fleſh, with all things that ſhall not be found in him and of him; God will judge the world by Chriſt, not by <hi>Moſes,</hi> nor by Angel nor by any other ſpirit; the Goſpel and ſpirit of Chriſt in his people, ſhall judge both Angels and men, ſpiritual and fleſhly wickedneſs.</p>
               <p>The ſpirit of judgement is found either in the natural or ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual man; the natural man being under the Law, hath a light
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:48979:31"/> within him to diſcern the things of the Law; his judgement reacheth only to the righteouſneſs of the Law, and to ſins againſt the Law; the ſpiritual man being freed from the Law in the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious righteouſneſs of Chriſt, is able to judge of all things, all Religions, ſpirits, kinds and conditions of life whatſoever; judgings do abound amongſt all men in this Age, but few have the true ſpirit or rule of judgement; Law, or form, or light within are the principles of judgement with moſt; with the ſpiritual man ſo far as he abides free in Chriſt, it is a ſmall thing to be judged by any of theſe, yea he judgeth not himſelf; therefore let all take heed with what ſpirit you judge, leſt you judge, and not by the Goſpel, nor in the Lord.</p>
               <p>The Prophets and <hi>John</hi> had a ſpirit of judgement, but they teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied alſo of righteouſneſs only by him that was to come; they called not the people to a redemption preſent or to be done in that Age, or by the light within every man; let this people bear teſtimony to that alone righteouſneſs as already fulfilled for us in him, and not call away from that unto another redemption to be done over again, of which no Prophets ſpake, that is, by the light within all men; and then ſhall true judgement be given unto them; till then they will but erre in judgement and ſtumble in viſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Perfection.</head>
               <p>His Principle matter is, That Perfection is that gift or light in every man by joyning to which he is made perfect; that God ſent his ſon into the world to preach perfection, a perfect example, which whoſo believe and follow him in it are made perfect; that nothing but perfection, that is, freedom from ſin in the body be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore death can give reſt and Redemption; that imperfection of righteouſneſs and gifts came in by the miniſtry of Antichriſt, and is of the Divel.</p>
               <p>The Goſpel myſtery ſaith, that Chriſt being the perfection of grace and truth, of life and righteouſneſs, came forth in fleſh, and therein on the Croſs put an end to the imperfect Miniſtry of the Law and Prophets, to the pollutions and imperfections of fleſh, and by one offering in his own perſon perfected for ever all that were ſanctified; he being the perfection of love, life, light, and righteouſneſs, ſlew in himſelf the enmity, the power of death, and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:48979:31"/> all that darkneſs and ſin that was by the Law; the Law could not give life, men could not obey, all creatures could not find out an Interceſſor; at this time Chriſt came forth in the glory of the Godhead, in the weakneſs of our manhood, that in the one he might bear all that was againſt us, by the other he might ſpoil and triumph over all for us; he was love and bowels to perfection, a Saviour to perfection; ſo that not by the Law without, nor light within, nor any other imagined or pretended perfection; but in him ye are compleat, who is the fulneſs of the God-head; in whoſe death you are dead and buried, and in him raiſed up into the heavenly liberty and perfection, if you do believe, though darkneſs, imperfections, &amp; fightings may yet remain in your fleſh; Chriſt firſt deſcended into the lower parts of the earth, our weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and death, that he might finiſh them in himſelf; after he aſcended far above all heavens, that he might fill all things, that he might make the Angels, life and death to miniſter, to be for his own; as it is ſaid, all are yours; this is perfection, yet hid; not in every man, but with Chriſt in God, and in the hearts of the children of faith.</p>
               <p>And if ſo, then was Chriſt in fleſh no more then a Preacher or example of perfection? was that fulneſs of the Godhead, that brightneſs of the fathers glory in him, no other then ſuch a light as God hath ſet up in every man? or was his bearing our ſins, and the wounds for iniquities no more, but to ſhew unto us how we ſhould bear them in our ſelves? then what preheminence had his perſon above <hi>Moſes, Noah</hi> and the reſt who were Preachers of righteouſneſs and perfection? or wherein is his Goſpel above the Law, which is a rule of perfection? or what were his ſufferings more then thoſe of <hi>Paul,</hi> who was in deaths often? let the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual judge which is the Doctrine of Perfection.</p>
               <p>Perfection is either that in the head, hid for us there until he ſhall appear, or a meaſure and earneſt thereof manifeſt in our bodies; according to the firſt, a believer overcomes, poſſeſſeth all things, is dead, raiſed up, and received by Chriſt into the glory of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.7. according to the other, a believer knows but in part, ſees, enjoyes, and propheſies but in part, and ſo is in im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection; wherefore let the Children in Chriſt know that they are ſaved and perfected in the Lord for ever, whileſt yet their ſeeings, prayings, and actings in the Lord are but in part; and let this people know, if they look away from that one offering
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:48979:32"/> in the head, and be not firſt perfected therein, that all other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection by the light within and utmoſt obedience will not ſtand them in ſtead in the laſt day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Obedience.</head>
               <p>The ſum of things ſpoken by him is, that to be guided in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the ſpirit or light within us, as Chriſt was by the ſpirit of the father in him, this is the righteouſneſs of Chriſt; and thus by the obedience of one are many made righteous: that the father calls for the ſame obedience of the believer, as of Chriſt; and the believer offers up himſelf in the ſame obedience Chriſt did; and ſo is the obedience of Chriſt and a believer one: that the creature is not made perfectly righteous by the obedience of Chriſt, till he comes to the ſame perfection of obedience that Chriſt did; and ſo he is made righteous no further then he obeys.</p>
               <p>If nothing ſhould be ſaid, the ſwelling pride of this ſpirit in lifting up it ſelf in an equal ſufficiency with the perſon of Chriſt, to drink the ſame cup, and offer up the ſame obedience for the purging away ſin, may hereby appear; yet I may not be ſilent in the cauſe of my Lord, although I am the leaſt in my fathers houſe. Although this Doctrine may have a glory with the ſublime wits of ſpeculative Pagans, who know not, or deign not to know any other way of approaching the Divine Glory then the way Chriſt did, that is, without a Mediator; yet unto the true Chriſtian who through many tribulations hath ſeen an end of all perfection, whither fleſhly luſts, works of the Law, or heights of Philoſophy, it is known to be but a depth of Satan; but who art thou Oh man that uttereſt theſe great words? haſt thou all the fulneſs of the God-head in thy ſelf, in the meaſure the man Jeſus had? haſt thou all thoſe treaſures of Light, wiſedom, and Power in the ſame fulneſs that he had? that thou canſt follow him into the perfection and glory of God, by the ſame way of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence he did; art thou able to bear the ſins of many, to ſuſtain the ſentence and terrible Majeſty of the Law in thy body, to encounter with all the Angels and powers of darkneſs, to lay down thy life for many, and take it up again? was not this and much more the obedience of Chriſt? was not he made perfect by theſe ſufferings? and doeſt thou think to come to perfection or the glory of God by doing the like, or not rather by believing he hath done all this for thee?</p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:48979:32"/>
               <p>Wherefore let it be known, that the ſpirit hath teſtified in Scriptures of two things in the obedience of Chriſt; a Myſtery to be believed, and an Example to be followed; Chriſt as Mediator, being the only perſon in whom all things pertaining to God and men, the repairing of the breach, and the making up of a bleſſed union between them were to be tranſacted, received into himſelf, and therein ſlew our old man, the enmity, and all the evils of the world, and being in the glory of the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> put an end in himſelf to the glory of the firſt, and in the place of all this brought forth in himſelf everlaſting righteouſneſs, liberty and peace, into and upon all them that believe; whereupon a believer may ſay, as I am in the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> where the Law, reaſon, and ſenſe bear rule, ſo I am in a Tabernacle of fleſh, an houſe of darkneſs, ſo I often neither feel, nor know, nor behold any redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, liberty, or peace; but as I am in the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> I neither know law, reaſon, nor ſenſe, fleſh, world, nor work, but Chriſt to be all in all; this is the myſtery to be believed, a myſtery hid from the ſpirit of this world, or the pureſt and cleareſt principle in the heart of the natural man; if this myſtery of Chriſt in his death were known to any as it is in him, Chriſt would appear to that man as a fulneſs of light and glory, in, through, and over all things; or were a believer known to himſelf or the world, as he is known in Chriſt to Chriſt, he would not be able to bear the world, nor the world him; therefore blind or worſe, are thoſe reproaches that are caſt upon this myſtery of the death of Chriſt, and redemption by it, as a knowing of Chriſt without, at <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> or after the fleſh; nothing brings forth Chriſt more as a ſpirit of wiſedom, power, and holineſs within me unto good works, then when I behold him as made righteouſneſs and ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication to me without work; whoſoever takes away the laſt, doth alſo take away the firſt, and at beſt hath no more but a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed likeneſs, or imagined ſhadow thereof.</p>
               <p>As Chriſt ſuffered for us in the fleſh, that the father in him as his head and life, might be revealed and glorified in him; ſo in the ſame ſpirit and mind ought the believer to ſuffer in the fleſh, that Chriſt in him as this head and life, might be glorified and manifeſt in him; thus is Chriſt's obedience an example to be followed; our dyings and perfectings in the body by obedience, when proceeding from our firſt being dead and perfected in the head by faith, ſo they are the precious ſavours and fruits of Chriſt and grace; but if dyings and obedience in us be made the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:48979:33"/> way unto perfection and juſtification in Chriſt, then they are no other but works of the Law, diſguiſed with names of Chriſt and ſpirit; as this people ſtand divided from the firſt, ſo am I divided from them, and ſo doth this teſtimony go forth againſt them.</p>
               <p>There are diverſities of operations, but the ſame ſpirit; his Doctrine ſaith, that we are perfectly juſtified by Chriſt's obedience, when we perform obedience in the ſame meaſure he did; if ſo, then the obedience of the man Jeſus and ours are no more one then the obedience of <hi>Paul</hi> and ours, that is, one in ſpirit, but two in operation; thus by his Doctrine, we are juſtified as much by the obedience of <hi>Paul,</hi> as of the man Chriſt, as to the opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; let him, and them, conſider if it be not ſo, and fear.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning good Works.</head>
               <p>His account is, that by obedience to the light which reproves of ſin, following it out of the world, and bringing forth the fruits of it, the creature comes into the good work or obedience of Chriſt, and ſo is by Chriſt redeemed; that by being diligent in this light, waiting and obedient therein, the believer is led into the obedience, ſufferings, tribulations, and temptations of Chriſt; that all the works and meaſures performed by the creature in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to this light, do all compleat but this one work of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures redemption.</p>
               <p>Where faith and unity with the head is loſt, no marvel if all the thoughts of that man run into confuſion; that the obedience or righteouſneſs in Chriſt for juſtification, and good works in us are one thing, his own words at large may manifeſt, if this ſhort account of them may not; and thereupon what foundation they build, I need ſay no more; only for the weaks ſake I ſhal ſpeak a word; Chriſt was in the beginning with God, that good Word whereby all things were made; the ſame word in fulneſs of time became fleſh in him that was the holy and juſt One, who in his own perſon eternally vanquiſhed all the evils of the world, and to the utmoſt fulfilled the holy and perfect work of God, for an everlaſting and only righteouſneſs upon all that believe; of the greatneſs whereof might I ſpeak, it is higher then the Heavens, deeper then the Sea, and the utmoſt bounds and ends thereof can no more be known, then can the heights and depths of him be known, that is, the holy one of Iſrael.</p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:48979:33"/>
               <p>And this is the one obedience, one righteouſneſs, one good work in one perſon, one in ſpirit, one in operation, never to be renewed more in any other; the ſame being not of a private nature, nor for a private ſpirit, but one for all; he that hath made of one blood all Nations of men, hath by one blood created anew out of all Nations, a people for himſelf; and if the natural heavens over us were ſpread forth at once, in length and breadth large enough to comprehend, preſerve, and nouriſh all Nations and all things therein; how much more ſhall that One righteouſneſs of Chriſt, which is one with himſelf, be as ſpiritual heavens large enough to take in, to cover and preſerve the ſecond creation, without any other to be added thereto, how low and narrow, yea, how unbelieving and unworthy are their thoughts and eſteem of the perſon and righteouſneſs of Chriſt, that think otherwiſe, I leave to be weighed.</p>
               <p>Through faith I come to read this moſt good and glorious work of God, and therein to underſtand how that this world and my old man or fleſh, with all the evils of both by the operation of the bleſſed Divinity in his body were aboliſhed in himſelfe through death, whilſt yet darkneſs, pollutions and fightings, and thereby heavineſs for a ſeaſon is felt in my fleſh; wherein I alſo reckon my ſelf to be as truly crucified and buried with him, through the operation of the Godhead, in the man Jeſus for me, as if the ſame had been done in me; and this is the myſtery of faith, and the praiſe thereof is great, but not before men, who eſteem of nothing but of what appears, or is ſeen, felt, or handled; and hence I think it neceſſary to give this warning, that all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches unto or converſes with the majeſty and glory of God by any redemption or operation of whatſoever ſpirit or light within, and all myſteries of light and perfection ſo reputed whatſoever where that bleſſed and eternal redemption in the perſon of Chriſt for us is excluded; I ſay through faith, that all ſuch are no other but ſome of the brighter ſparks of Satans fires, kindled on purpoſe to lead the creature to God by ſuch a door, as wherein he will be unto it a conſuming fire; can two walk together except they be agreed? that man knows neither what God is, nor himſelf, that thinks to attain, or to have attained the glorious preſence of God by ſpirit within him, who is not firſt reconciled through the propitiation of grace in the blood of Jeſus.</p>
               <p>If any man ask (as they often do) how can Redemption be
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:48979:34"/> where it is not witneſſed, where conſcience chargeth of ſin? my anſwer is, who ſhall lay any thing to my charge, it is Chriſt that died? my witneſſes are the ſpirit, water, and blood; the ſpirit of Revelation ſhining in my heart, and the power of his death and redemption in part manifeſt in my body; whilſt heart and fleſh, that is reaſon, and ſenſe and law witneſs againſt me, yet Chriſt and grace is greater then all, let him alone ſpeak, let theſe be ſilent.</p>
               <p>But if they ask, to believe redemption whilſt ſin in me, is not this the unreaſonable hope? No, the father laid our ſins upon Chriſt to take them away, whilſt we were yet enemies that he might commend his great love to us, this was reaſonable with God; the Son rent our ſins from off him in his own body on the tree, becauſe he could not be held of them, this was reaſonable with Chriſt; the ſpirit bears witneſs that all things are finiſhed, ſin, death, and the fleſh, in the body of Chriſt unto him that works not but believes on him, that juſtifies the ungodly, this witneſs is reaſonable; through faith I receive Chriſt into my ſelf, and am received into him, and through this oneneſs am made righteouſneſs, life, and light, in the Lord, whilſt yet I am in many darkneſſes and deaths as to ſenſe and feeling; and this is reaſon as in the mind of God, and according to the myſtery of Chriſt; that doctrine or ſpirit how myſterious ſoever in words or ſh<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w, that teacheth redemption to be by the operation of the ſpirit within us, and not by that alone operation of God in the man Chriſt Jeſus, is indeed the excellency and height of man's reaſon and thoughts, but a fearful contradiction to that higher reaſon, or rather that bleſſed myſtery of grace that appeared in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Whereas he ſaith, that all the works and meaſures performed by the creature in obedience to the light within, do all compleat the one work of the creatures redemption; to this I ſhall only ſay, how is the day of free grace ſet upon us, and how are the thick clouds of Legality and miſterious reaſon ſpread over us, if this may be received for truth; and let me only remember you of the words of <hi>Luther</hi> a man wiſer and mightier in Chriſt then I, which follows.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>It was indeed a great glory that <hi>Abraham</hi> received circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion at the commandment of God, that he was endued with excellent vertues, that he obeyed God in all things, but all this availeth nothing, to righteouſneſs before God; the excellent
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:48979:34"/> deeds and vertues of <hi>Abraham</hi> were not the cauſe that he was counted righteous before God; ſo the following of the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of, doth not make us righteous before God; for to that there is a more excellent price required, which is neither the righteouſneſs of man, nor yet of the Law, here we muſt have Chriſt; how? not by works, but by faith; therefore as there is a great difference between Chriſt bleſſing or redeeming and Chriſt working or giving example; wherefore we muſt ſeperate the believing and the working <hi>Abraham</hi> as far aſunder as there is diſtance betwixt heaven and earth; <hi>Abraham</hi> believing in Chriſt is altogether a divine perſon, the child of God, inheritour of the world, conqueror of ſin, death, the world, and the Divel; therefore he cannot be praiſed and magnified enough; let us not ſuffer this faithful <hi>Abraham</hi> to lye hid in his grave, as he is hid from the Jews, but let us highly extol and magnify him, and let us fill both heaven and earth with his name; ſo that in reſpect of the faithful <hi>Abraham</hi> we ſee nothing at all in the working <hi>Abraham;</hi> for when we ſpeak of this faithful <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> we are in heaven, but afterwards doing thoſe things which the working <hi>Abraham</hi> did, which were carnal and earthly, and not divine and heavenly (but as they were given unto him of God) we are among men in earth; the believing <hi>Abraham</hi> filleth both heaven and earth; ſo every Chriſtian through his faith filleth both heaven and earth, ſo that beſides it he ought to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold nothing.</q> Thus far his words. Good works or the works of God in us are in compariſon of the righteouſneſs in Chriſt but carnal, like as <hi>Abraham's</hi> good works (a thing worthy of note) are but accounted fleſh in compariſon of the righteouſneſs of Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.1, 2.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Election and Reprobation.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>He ſaith, that the light in every man which reproves of ſin is Chriſt, and is the election, elect ſeed, the mercy of God placed in all men, that this light being believed and followed, till by it a man be changed and purged from the oldneſs and luſts of fleſh, to the newneſs of the ſpirit then he comes to the election, or to be ſelected.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Truth ſaith, that in every man which reproves of ſin is not Chriſt but the Law; by the Law is the knowledge of ſin; that Chriſt the Elect and beloved of God is he in whom the purpoſes,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:48979:35"/> promiſes, counſels, and all the works of God were laid up and known unto God from before the world began; Chriſt was from the beginning the common ſeed or Father, in whoſe loines God in his foreknowledge beheld, and in his love chooſe a ſeed or ofspring whom he would beget of his own will by his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</p>
               <p>God that ſeparated the Jews from all other Nations only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he loved them; that ſaid of the children of <hi>Iſaac</hi> being not yet born, <hi>Jacob</hi> have I loved, but <hi>Eſau</hi> have I hated; that called them his beloved, which were not beloved; that ſeparated <hi>Paul</hi> a perſecuter from his mothers womb; that hath mercy on whom he will have mercy; the ſame God hath foreknown and choſen and loved a people in Chriſt the beloved, who though for the preſent, as concerning the Goſpel they be enemies through wicked works; yet as touching the election they are beloved for Chriſt's ſake; <hi>you have not choſen me, but I have choſen you: If I be lifted up from the earth, I will draw all men unto me;</hi> Chriſt drawed up all his own in his body into himſelf in love; this love ſhed forth into our hearts, draws us up in love into him again; thus we love him becauſe he loved us firſt: the father gave a people to the Son from everlaſting, and ſaw and loved them in him before the world was; the Son came forth to manifeſt and make way for this love through his righteouſneſs down unto men; the ſpirit reveals that love, and by Chriſt leads us unto the father; thus redemption and ſanctification are both fruits of that love and election that was given us in Chriſt before the world began: by receiving Chriſt the Image of the father I come indeed to know his love and election, but he both lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, elected and redeemed me in Chriſt the head, before I was. Wherefore they that deny election, and redemption, until the creatures obedience to the light within, do meaſure the thoughts and waies of the unſearchable goodneſs of God with the low and narrow thoughts and waies of man; being zealous indeed for the righteouſneſs of God according to the Law, but darkning and denying the glorious righteouſnes of God as in Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the New birth.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>He ſaith, that by abiding in the ſeed or light within every man,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:48979:35"/> thereby the old man is put off with his deeds: that they who are guided by this light (called by him the eternal ſpirit) do follow God as he goes out of one form into another; all others ſtay therein after God is gone, as ſeeing but the outſide or form only; that they who joyned to the light within that reproves of ſin, to be led by it, are and ever were hated and perſecuted of all others.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His ſilence throughout of that more excellent and truly miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious way of crucifying the body of ſin in the perſon of Chriſt, whoſe body and blood is by him made as no more but figuers of the body and blood within, that is, the light within all men, this doth ſufficiently manifeſt his mind and principle, and the end whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it leads, unto mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> to preſs through unto God by an attonement and mediation to be made in our bodies, that is, obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the light within.</p>
               <p>The new creature is not a Jew, one ſeeking righteouſneſs by the Law, either in the letter or conſcience, nor a Gentile, one thinking to know, comprehend, and worſhip God by the light or wi<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>edom of the natural man, but a man in Chriſt, dead, buried, and riſen with him into heavenly places above the world, ſin, and death, by faith alone without work, that is, before theſe things be manifeſt or wrought in his members: alſo he is one in whom Chriſt dwels by faith, &amp; ſo made partaker of the divine Nature, that ſpirit which the world ſees not, hath not, nor by any light they have can find it out, the world's light is a candle from the Lord, ſaying do this and live; the ſpirit of the new creature is the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, ſaying, I have done it, only believe and live. According to the myſterie of faith, the new man is in heart and ſpirit gone out of all the world, and is in heaven perfectly juſtified, redeemed, and ſaved, but in a way above ſenſe and feelings, yet ſeen by faith; according to preſent manifeſtation he hath the ſpirit of Chriſt whereby he ſees, knows, and enjoys in part thoſe perfect things, in Chriſt, till they be fully revealed; if any man boaſts of the firſt, that he is redeemed by Chriſt, and hath not the other, that he lives in ſome meaſure after the ſpirit, that man's boaſting is in vain; likewiſe if any man glories of the ſpirit, that he walks in the ſpirit, in mortifyings of the fleſh, neglect of the body, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, neceſſities, labours, ſtripes, priſons, in wearineſs, pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, watchings often, in hunger, thirſt, cold and nakedneſs, and yet hath not that which is above all theſe, the heavenly and glorious righteouſneſs in Chriſt by faith, let ſuch know, their
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:48979:36"/> glorying is but in the fleſh, and ſhall not profit before the Lord.</p>
               <p>Concerning miniſtrations, and following God out of one into another, it may be ſaid, that the Law, Prophets and <hi>John</hi> were miniſtrations typing and teſtifying of things in the heavens to come, and ſo were done away; Chriſt was the ſubſtance of heavenly things themſelves, and ſo his miniſtration remains to this day; as that of the letter was perfected and given at once by one man at mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> yet to be continued till he came who was the end thereof, ſo this miniſtration of righteouſneſs and ſpirit was perfected and given at once by one man Chriſt, on the Croſs, yet to ſtand in force, by divers meaſures and manifeſtations of ſpirit and truth to be revealed and brought to light till he comes again, and takes his people unto himſelf; now of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe manifeſtations of ſpirit, ſome are true, ſome deceiveable; for diſcerning of which we have a good rule, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.4.5. now there are diverſities of gifts, but the ſame ſpirit, and differences of adminiſtration, but the ſame Lord; adminiſtrations of light &amp; truth, though diverſe as to the meaſure and manner of the gifts, yet if agreeing in one Chriſt, are all good and uſeful in their ſeaſons; to follow God into the pureſt and beſt is a glory upon them that do it; to be left behind may be weakneſs in them that are Chriſt's, but is wickedneſs in the world.</p>
               <p>On the other hand, thoſe pretended Miniſtries or Angels of light whatſoever, that do teach another Jeſus, another ſpirit, another faith, that is, redemption by obedience to the light in every man, ſuch are not of God; and to call that a miniſtration of ſpirit and life is no more true, then to call the Law ſo; the light in every man and the Law in the letter being the ſame: if any ſhall leave Chriſt crucified as but a figure of redemption, and ſhall follow the light in the conſcience, as the ſubſtance thereof, let him know, out of Chriſt crucified is no more ſacrifice for ſin, nor will God be found but as conſuming fire.</p>
               <p>If any ſhall think that redemption without by the blood of Chriſt is done away when that by the light within is perfected; to ſuch I ſay, till mortality be ſwallowed up of life, and the body now dead becauſe of ſin be thereby freed from all corruption, until then I judge both Chriſt crucified for us, and the faith therein will be of neceſſary and bleſſed uſe.</p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:48979:36"/>
               <p>To what he ſaith of perſecution, this may be ſaid; they that followed after the ſpirit and teachings thereof were indeed al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies perſecuted by the children of the fleſh and letter; but they that ſought righteouſneſs by the Law and the principles thereof in the conſcience, were thoſe children of the fleſh by whom the blood of them that were after the ſpirit hath been ſhed in every Age; was not the blood of Saints formerly in <hi>England, France,</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> ſhed for bearing teſtimony to the righteouſneſs of faith alone without works.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the Baptiſm of Chriſt from that the world ſo calls.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>His profeſſion herein is, that the Baptiſm of Chriſt is (I underſtand the light within all men) by which a man being baptiſed into his death, buried with him unto the world, its waies and worſhips, loves and friendſhips, ſo he is baptiſed with the Batiſm of Chriſt. That Baptiſms of water as now are carnal in the world, about which all are divided and contending that are in them, being gone out into the world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Baptiſm of Chriſt is that in Chriſt wherewith he was bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed in his own perſon, not for himſelf, but for us, and we in him as in our head, that is, when together with his own body through death he put off our old man and all the ſins of our fleſh at once in himſelf, by whoſe baptiſm our ſins, death, our fleſh, and all this world were really, yet in a myſtery dead and buried with him, and as by an overflowing River waſhed clean away by himſelf, before either the faith or power thereof was known or wrought in us; this baptiſm is a myſtery unknown to all Law-workers whatſoever, whither the more myſtical or literal ſort of them, who know no higher baptiſm then by deeds of holineſs in obedience to a light within or letter without; alſo to the maſters of reaſon who know no other baptiſm then by refined principles and exerciſes of morality; this is the baptiſm of juſtification and ſanctification in the head, wherewith we were waſhed, ſanctified, and juſtified in him even before we were; the ſame being revealed in us by faith ſprinkles from our hearts an evil conſcience, and then the ſpirit of him dwelling in our mortall fleſh waſheth our bodies with pure water; thus the baptiſm of Chriſt is one,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:48979:37"/> firſt in him perfected for us, afterwards in meaſures revealed in us.</p>
               <p>Whereas he concludes only baptiſms of water to be carnal waſhings; I ſay both baptiſms of water in what form ſoever with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the ſpirit, are carnal; and alſo all baptiſms by what name ſoever, particularly that of retirement out of all things into the light in every man, where that Baptiſm in the head by the offering up of his body once for all is denied, will be found to be but carnal, that is, ſerving to the waſhing off the filth of the fleſh only; take away that baptiſm in the head, wherein the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> with his diſobedience and death was crucified and purged away, and all other baptiſms whither by reformations within, or fair ſhews without, whither by the Law, letter, water, or whatſoever will be found equally carnal, equally inſufficient to preſent the ſinner holy and without ſpot to God. His judgement againſt all indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent baptiſms, that they are gone out into the world ſavours of a ſpirit as divided and carnal as they can be whom he judgeth ſo; are they carnal that judge and contend for one form againſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and are not they as carnal that judge and contend againſt all forms, becauſe not in their form of doctrine, and poſture, and way; when Chriſt ſhall ſit as Judge, as there ſhall be no advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to them that are in one form more then another, ſo neither to them that are gone out of all profeſſed forms; but to be found in him who is the head, is more then all.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the Lords Supper.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe things are ſaid, the true end of the Supper is moderation, to keep men from exceſs and luſt in eating aad drinking; that to do it in remembrance of his death till he comes, is to eat in fear without luſt till he comes to govern in the the creature himſelf, to keep out of luſt in all, and this is the reſtoring and reconciling to God the creation by Chriſt. That Chriſt's Diſciples were not changed, nor he born in them when he gave them this commandement, nor was Chriſt yet appeared to thoſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers among whom the Apoſtles continued it. That to eat of his body is to diſcern his body to be the body of all creatures, and to fill all htings.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:48979:37"/>
               <p>How is the Goſpel-myſtery become a doctrine of bare mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality with this people? to ſee God in all things, to diſcern him as the body and vertue of every creature, and to uſe all things in moderation; what is this more then the purer principles and practiſes of Pagan divinity? is this all the effect, all the end of the blood of Chriſt?</p>
               <p>He that appointed this Supper, ſaid, drink ye all of it, for this is my blood of the new Teſtament which is ſhed for many, for the remiſſion of ſins: Chriſt as he gave his fleſh for the life of the world, that is, as he aboliſhed death and brought forth life to light therein for us, ſo he is the true ſpiritual paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over which was ſacrificed for us, ſo his death is a myſtery, whoſoever can look therein may ſee the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> with all his deeds, the world with all its works &amp; all old things done away therein; traditions of men, and rudiments of the world ſhews of wiſedom, wil-worſhip and humility were tares the Lord foreſaw would ſpring up in the Churches from the root of reaſon and the Law; that they might avoid the ſame, he ordained the Supper for a rudiment to all that ſhould have need thereof, to be as a figure of his death, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in of the crucifying of fleſh with all the glory and workes thereof.</p>
               <p>Wherefore eating the fleſh of Chriſt is to be eſteemed, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as any naturall thing, as the Jews did, nor as any mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral thing, as this deluded people doe; but a divine and heavenly myſterie, that is, to believe, and rejoyce in Chriſt crucified, as made the remiſſion of ſinnes, the deſtruction of death, the grace, and the end of this world and all evils therein unto us; likewiſe the diſcerning the Lord's body therein is not a bare ſpeculation of Chriſt or the divinity, as filling all things (for the natural man by that of God in him may know ſo much) to diſcerne together with his dead body our ſins, our old man, the Law and all perfection, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by nature, morality or the Law, to be already dead, buried, and aboliſhed in his grave, and our ſelves raiſed up into the life, liberty, and righteouſneſs of Chriſt in him; this is the uſe of eating the Lord's body; if any be become ſo vain in imagination as to think it is no more then the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:48979:38"/> of temperance and moderation to be performed by us, let us know that it is the blood of the New Teſtament for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſins.</p>
               <p>That Chriſt comming in the creature, governing it him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, ſo reconciles it to God, is true indeed according to reaſon, the Law, and this people, but in the perſon of Chriſt through death did God reconcile the World to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; Chriſt revealed in a man is not that he may recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile, but being reconciled that he may bring him to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. But canſt thou poore ſorry ſinfull man beare in thy body the juſtice of the Law, the puniſhment of thy ſinnes, the ſhedding of thy blood, and raiſe up thy ſelf again, and through thy obedience come forth out of all thy ſins before the majeſty of God, in that perfect and ſpotleſs righteouſneſs that he ſhall ſee no ſin in thee? and if thou ſayeſt, Chriſt in thee can do all this; I anſwer, if thou believeſt not God hath already re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled thee to himſelfe by the death of his Sonne, that ſpirit that thou thinkeſt doth reconcile in thee, will be found moſt wicked and provoking deluſion, except Chriſt died in vain.</p>
               <p>That Chriſt's Diſciples were not changed, nor he born in them, when he appointed this Supper, and that Chriſt had not appeared to the Believers with whom the Apoſtles continued it, are both contrary to truth; they were clean every whit through the word he had ſpoken, or as in him, and their bodies the Temple of the holy Ghoſt, though they were as yet carnall and ignorant of the more ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall truths; ſo the Church of Chriſt is pure and beautifull as in him, whilſt fleſhly and weake in many things as in themſelves; rejoyce in Chriſt, as your liberty in whom you are made free; let him dwell in you crucifying your fleſh, and manifeſting his life; wait for his great and laſt appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to reign over all; of which day it ſhall not need to be ſaid, lo here, lo there, but as lightning from Eaſt to Weſt it ſhall beare witneſs of it ſelf in and over the whole creation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:48979:38"/>
               <head>Concerning Redemption.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>He ſaith, that redemption is not of ſinners that take delight in ſin, but of the light within, that is it which wants redemption; and of th<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> it is ſaid, he took not on him the nature of Angels but the ſeed of</hi> Abraham. <hi>That this light or ſeed as it is raiſed to reign in us above all, ſo it is redeemed, and ſo is the creature made free from the law of ſin, and no redemption while this is in priſon, and not brought above all our luſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How hath the blackneſs and darkneſſe of mount <hi>Sinai</hi> covered the heart of this man? how are the abounding riches of grace, the fulneſſe of the Mediator, and the power of his Croſſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved at once into the light or Law written in the heart of every man; but the ſpirit of faith ſaith otherwiſe, Man for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be a living Image of the glory of God, but fallen ſhort of his glory, ſeparate from the life of God in ſpirit, ſoul and body fallen into darkneſſe, death, and the curſe, this was it that wanted redemption, that was redeemed in Chriſt; <hi>ſcarcely for a righteous man would one die, yet paradventure for a good man ſome would dare to die, Rom.</hi> 5. to give ones life to ſave a righteous man, the heart and love of man may be enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to that; but herein divine love appeared beyond all number, meaſure, or the heart of man, in that whilſt yet ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners we were reconciled to God by the death of his Son, and raiſed up together into heavenly places, before we either knew deſired or ſought after the ſame; but is the light, or ſeed, or Chriſt under the Law, ſin or curſe? or needs he to be redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med or ſaved from theſe? the children are pertakers of fleſh and blood, therefore Chriſt pertook of fleſh, and bringing his divine nature thereinto, he crucified and aboliſhed our ſins and death out of it, and ſo preſented us to God a ſanctified, cleanſed, and perfected people in himſelf, before we did o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey or believe, or were; therefore let us ſay with joy, in the Lord we have righteouſneſs and ſtrength, in the Lord are we juſtified and do glory.</p>
               <p>To what he ſaith, as the light within is raiſed and reigns,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:48979:39"/> ſo is both it and the creature redeemed and no more; the Law of commandments hath dominion over the fleſh as long as it lives; a greater Law came forth, Chriſt in fleſh, and there in put an end both to the Law and the fleſh; thus we are delivered from the Law by the body of Chriſt, and are joyned to one husband, not to the Law and Chriſt, but to Chriſt alone; according to the inward man we dwell in the curtains of <hi>Solomon,</hi> in the liberty and reſt of Chriſt as in him, while according to the fleſh we are in the tents of <hi>Kedar,</hi> temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and dark, and weak as in our ſelves; thus in the dead body of Chriſt I am dead and buried unto the Law, ſin, death, and the whole world, and raiſed in Chriſt; and this is my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, which neither the principles of reaſon, nor mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, nor Law, nor light of conſcience can diſcern and teach, but the alone light of the glorious Goſpel of Chriſt ſhining into the heart.</p>
               <p>Wherefore there is a redemption that is according to reaſon, and a redemption that is in a myſtery; to return to that light and purity by obedience, from which we are fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len by diſobedience, this is redemption according to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, the Law, the light within, and the judgement of this people; herein is no myſtery, for the wiſe men of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then wrote of it, and preſſed after it; all Nations imagine ſuch a redemption; but that the fall ſhould be amended, and the creature reſtored, not into the ſtate of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> but a greater and better, the righteouſneſſe of God; and all this without any vertue or work, or ſervice on our parts, but by the alone operation of the bleſſed God-head in the man Jeſus; this is that myſtery hid in God, whereof the higheſt ſpeculations, the cleareſt light of that candle in the naturall man is utterly ignorant and unlearned; otherwiſe it were not a myſtery, if any light whatſoever ſet up in man by his firſt creation could have found it out; wherefore to live to the Law, that thou mayſt live to God, is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption that reaſon and this people teach; I through the Law am dead to the Law, that I may live unto God, is the Redemption that brings glory, the other will end in death.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:48979:39"/>
               <head>Concerning Juſtification, Sanctification, and Mortification.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>He affirms, that to walk in the ſpirit and not fulfil the luſts of the fleſh; or Chriſt fulfilling the Law in us, or the ſpirit morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying and ſanctifying and ſo fulfilling the Law in us, this is juſtification, ſanctification and mortification, and theſe are one, and ſo a man is juſtified, as he is ſanctified, and mortified, and no further.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Will you adventure your ſouls upon ſuch a juſtification as this, therein to appeare before God? if it be not too late to tell you, know that juſtification is a free gift already prepared and wrought for ſinners, in the perſon of him who is greater then Angels or men; who being the fulneſſe of all divine vertue and perfection, did thereby as by an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing flood upon his Croſs beare away our ſinnes and death, all the evils of this world, and buried them in his grave for ever; Angels though great and mighty in power could not ſave; the Law being greater then they could not give life, Chriſt came forth mightier then all, gathered together in himſelf the enmity, death, and Law, and all things that were againſt us, nailed them to his Croſs, and took all out of the way gloriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in himſelf; and ſo was that ſaying fulfilled, his voice then ſhoak the earth.</p>
               <p>He that believes this truly, according to his faith, ſo is it done unto him; the Chriſtian as believing is a man in Heaven, in Chriſt, ſit down in reſt, liberty and perfection in Chriſt; as wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king righteouſneſs, he is on earth, groaning after reſt, liberty, and perfection.</p>
               <p>But can there be Reſt and liberty where there is a groaning for it? yea, oh man, as well as <hi>Paul</hi> could be preſent in ſpirit where he was abſent in body; whilſt at home in the body we are abſent from the Lord, yet by faith we are preſent in the Lord; things of nature are taken in by reaſon or ſenſe; reaſon hath knowledge and communion with things before the ſenſe feeles or taſtes them; ſo the things of the ſpirit are taken in by faith or ſpiritual ſenſe; through faith the believer hath
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:48979:40"/> communion with ſpiritual things, before they be in their power and fulneſſe attained by ſenſe and feeling; the myſtery of grace in Chriſt is not limited, yet love of God and righteouſneſſe of Chriſt are not more or leſſe for the Believer, becauſe the manifeſtations thereof in him are ſo; the vail is rent, ſin finiſhed, all old things are paſſed away, but by faith I underſtand it to be ſo, as in Chriſt my head, and therein am juſtified; the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation thereof in my ſelf I wait for, and therein is my ſanctification as in my members; take away that juſtification in Chriſt for you, and all ſanctifications by obedience to the light within will profit you no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the Law.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The things of note ſaid by him are, Law is the miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the letter without, the Goſpel or miniſtration of the ſpirit is the ſame Law, but written in the heart of all men; they that believe Chriſt fulfilled the Law for us in his own perſon, and what we do he makes it accepted with the father, as though we did performe all that is required, none ſuch know his commands in ſpirit; that righteouſneſſe by faith is when the Law is performed in us by workes in ſpirit; righteouſneſſe by workes is when the Law is done by us without life and ſpirit; that the offering and blood without could make nothing perfect, that within being more pure and perfect; and that the Law in the conſcience is anſwered by the reſurrection of Chriſt within.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Are the Law and Goſpel the ſame? aske the wounded ſpirit beſet with the terrours of the Law of God, who lie under the ſharpeſt ſenſe of the Law, and can give the beſt account thereof? whither redemption was finiſhed in One, the perſon of Chriſt alone, or yet to be done in many, the perſons of all the redeemed, let the Scripture with the ſpirit be your light and rule until the day de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare.</p>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:48979:40"/>
               <p>The holy, juſt, and perfect will of God revealed to the world, firſt: by that in the conſcience, after upon Tables of ſtone, reproving for ſin, and requiring righteouſneſs by obedience, whether to the Letter without, or Light within; this is the miniſtration of death, mighty to kill, becauſe it was the working Covenant; weak to give life, becauſe it was not the Mediatour.</p>
               <p>Chriſt the fulneſs of all heavenly things, came forth in fleſh; and being in lengths and breadths, ſufficient for that purpoſe, did in himſelf fulfill what the Law required, and ſuſtaine all the Law had to charge upon us, and ſo in himſelf, put an end to the Law, for all that ſhould believe: that which requires works to be wrought in us, as the way to attaine righteouſneſs, whether it be Letter with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, or Light within, it is the Law; and herein do all the falſe and fleſhly Religions of the world agree in one: the Pagan ſeeks perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by his Law, natural Reaſon and Vertue; the Turk by his Alcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran; the Jew by <hi>Moſes;</hi> the Monke by the Rule of his Order; the Spiritual Papiſt, by mortification of the Spirit; and this People by perfect obedience to the Light within, that is, the Law; in this all are one, all ſeeking righteouſneſs by work in the fleſh, in obedience to Tradition, or Letter, or Spirit: The Law is a great light manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all fleſh and the deeds thereof, a great Lord ruling over all fleſh as long as it lives: Chriſt came forth greater than the Law, crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the fleſh, and the body of death in himſelf, and thereby put an end to the dominion of the Law, unto all that believe; thus in his Croſſe, I am dead to all things, and they to me.</p>
               <p>Whereas he ſaith, they know not his Commands in Spirit, who ſay, Chriſt fulfilled the Law for us in his own perſon, or that he makes what we do accepted with the Father; I ask of him, and of all in his perſwaſion; Can yee paſs through the depths of Sin, Death and the Curſe, that he paſſed through? yee neither know the Law, nor what ſpirit yee are of; Can yee bring forth the works of obedience, an incorruptible righteouſneſs, in your corruptible bodies, anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that pure Law, and moſt pure God, before whom <hi>Moſes</hi> did fear and quake, and <hi>Abraham</hi> by works could not glory, and no fleſh can be juſtified? were not all we like ſheep gone aſtray, and the Lord hath laid on him the iniquity of us all, the chaſtiſement of our peace was upon him, and by his ſtripes we are healed? where this is truly and purely believed, Revelations of Chriſt are moſt deſirable and glorious; where this is excluded, all pretended approaches to God, Revelations of God, or perfections of obedience, will be but
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:48979:41"/> as hotter fires, to conſume firſt your faith and intereſt in Chriſt, and after, your precious ſouls, with all your labour, and pains, and works.</p>
               <p>To what he ſaies, the bloud within makes perfect, that without could not; let it be ſaid, the bloud of the Man Chriſt, through the eternal Spirit working therein, became the death of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> with all his deeds, and all the evils that came in by him; ſo with him am I already dead and freed from ſin, as in him the Head; as this my death and freedome in him does reveale it ſelf in me, ſo I dye daily as in my earthly members. If by the bloud within, be intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this; that as the bloud of Bulls and Goats, was a figure of the bloud of Chriſt, ſo his bloud, was but a figure, of bloud or Spirit within us; then know aſſuredly, that as the bloud offered in the firſt Tabernacle, was offered without the Holieſt, though within the Tabernacle; ſo the bloud within, all purifyings by the light within, will be found to be but the bloud without, that is, offered without the veyle, without the Holieſt, though within your Perſons.</p>
               <p>But is not the Spirit ſufficient in power to redeem from ſin, by his work within us? let this be ſaid as of uſe, in moſt things that have been ſpoken; the power of the Spirit is unſearchable, and unlimited, but the myſtery of his Will is declared in Chriſt; that not by Spirit alone, but by Spirit and Bloud, and that in one man, he has redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and purged all the evils that came by the offence of one: of old God filled Heaven and Earth, yet he would be known and ſought only in Jeruſalem; nothing could comprehend the God head, yet the fulneſs of it dwelt in Chriſt bodily; ſo the Spirit dwells in all his people, yet through the bloud of the Man Chriſt alone, did God chuſe to go forth in his power, to the aboliſhing of our death, and manifeſting eternal freedome for us: ſo when it is ſaid, yee are ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified, redeemed, and ſaved by God, by Grace, by the name of Chriſt, by the Spirit of our God; we are to underſtand, that the Name, and Grace, and Spirit of God, went forth againſt our ſins and death in the bloud of Jeſus, and thereby did them away forever; which by faith we behold, and as we behold, we are changed into the ſame Image, from glory to glory, by the Spirit of the Lord.</p>
               <p>Wherefore the proper uſe of the Law, is firſt to bridle civil tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, and then to reveale and encreaſe ſpiritual tranſgreſſions; the Law is a Light, which revealeth not the Grace of God, not righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs and life, but ſin and death, wrath and judgement; and as in Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> the thundring, lightning, the thick and dark cloud,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:48979:41"/> the hill ſmoaking and flaming, and all that terrible ſhew did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice nor quicken the children of Iſrael, but terrified and aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them, and ſhewed how unable they were with all their purity and holineſs to abide the Majeſty of God; ſo the Law in its true uſe, doth nothing elſe but reveale ſin, work wrath, and bring into deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration, and here it hath an end, and ought to go no further: the uſe of the Goſpel, is to reveale the end of the Law, of ſin and wrath in the death of Chriſt, and the righteouſneſs, peace, and love of God, brought forth for us in him.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>I ſhall adde an obſervation of <hi>Luther;</hi> of this difference between the Law and Goſpel, there is nothing to be found in the Books of Monks, Cannoniſts, and School men, no nor in the Books of the ancient Writers; there was a wonderful ſilence many years as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching this difference, in all Schools and Churches; and this brought mens conſciences into great danger, for unl<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſs the Goſpel be plainly diſcerned from the Law, tru-doctrine cannot be kept ſound and uncorrupt; but if this difference be well known, it is an eaſie matter to diſcern faith from works, Chriſt from <hi>Moſes,</hi> and all politick works; for all things without Chriſt, are the Miniſtry of death, for the puniſhing of the wicked.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Chriſt Jeſus.</head>
               <p>HIs Faith is, that Chriſt humbled himſelf and became obedient unto death, that he might become a living example to all Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations; that the Light within every man, un<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ted and followed will lead unto Chriſt, and will reveale the power and God-head, and ſo the Light within, is the ſure word of Propheſie.</p>
               <p>The word of Faith ſaies, that Chriſt being the brightneſs of the inviſible God, came forth in fleſh, and being the eternal word, wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and power of God, and ſo having obtained a name and ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy above all other Lords; he put an end to the Law, Sin and Death, and the dominion thereof over us in his Croſſe, that he might bring forth Grace, Righteouſneſs, and Life, for us in himſelf, that ſo we being delivered out of the hands of our enemies, might ſerve him without fear; and is this no more than a living example to you? and if ſo, can ye after his example, break through the gates of ſin, wrath and the grave, and make your acceſs unto God through all, as he did? is ſo great a myſtery of Faith as this, become no more with you than a lofty imagination of Reaſon, onely enlivened with an active ſpirit of bondage?</p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:48979:42"/>
               <p>That not the Light within every man, but the word of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Prophets, and the ſpirit of Revelation, ſhining according to their Teſtimony, is that which leads to the Lord Jeſus: the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible divinity cannot be ſeen nor approached unto, but in the Mediatour, the Man Chriſt, ſo Chriſt is the image of the invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible God; the unſearchable Myſtery of Chriſt, is brought to light by the Goſpel, and to be learned by the Spirit, ſo the Scriptures are the Image of Chriſt; he that ſhall ſeek for God out of the Humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Chriſt, he ſhall looſe both God and himſelf; ſo he that to find out Chriſt, ſhall go to the Light within every man, and not to the Teſtimony of them, who ſpake of him what they had ſeen and heard he may come to behold him as the Law-giver, and Judge, but as a Juſtifier and Saviour he cannot know him: The Light within all men, may find out the God-head; but the Myſtery of Grace and Love, cannot be known but by that Spirit, that blowes where and when he liſts. Would the light within have ſhewed you the Attone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Redemption, the bloud and ſacrifice, or have put theſe words in your mouth?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning the Miniſtry of Chriſt.</head>
               <p>HE ſaies, the Miniſters of Chriſt have the Word in them, and ſo declare it to others; that they Preach not for hire or gain; that they are perſecuted of the world.</p>
               <p>He ſaies rightly; that is a Miniſtry of Chriſt; but Miniſters of Righteouſneſs, are of Satan, or of Chriſt; zealouſly to affect, to compaſs Sea and Land, to make fair ſhewes in the fleſh, to be as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Law, blameleſs, to preach freely, ſuffer labour, ſtripes, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonments: Satans Miniſters may be herein transformed as the Miniſters of Chriſt: wherefore Miniſtryes are to be judged by their Spirit, and Spirits by Doctrines: If an Angel from Heaven, if any Perſons coming forth in the wiſdome, holineſs, power, and glory of an Angel, ſhall not confeſs that Chriſt was made Sin and a Curſe, and the end of both through his death unto us, let them be accurſed; their Doctrine takes away the bleſſing of <hi>Abraham,</hi> which is in Chriſt, and brings men again under the Curſe of the Law, which by Chriſt is aboliſhed to all that truly believe: I am jealous that the Teachers of the People for the greateſt part, are carnal, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal, and but in the Letter, and walking as men: yet the Lord
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:48979:42"/> has his choſen ones among them: I am as jealous that the Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of this People, are the Miniſters of that darkneſs and wroth, by which God will puniſh this faithleſs, perverſe, and back-ſliding Generation: Let thy Spirit of Grace be poured forth upon thy Sons and Daughters, and the Spirit of errour and uncleanneſs, ſhall be revealed and caſt out.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Concerning Free-Will.</head>
               <p>HE ſaies, the Light within men, which reproves the evil deeds, is that Will of God by which we are ſanctified, and ſaved; that in every man which ſhewes him his ſin, and reproves for it, is Free-Grace: This Light in every man is the Free-will, which is free to God, and free from ſin.</p>
               <p>If the firſt be ſo, then is the death of Chriſt of no effect, wherein the whole bleſſed Will of God was done, by which Will we are ſanctified through his Body: how is Chriſt crucified become fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhneſs to you, who whilſt to your ſelves and others, you have a ſhew of humility, are vainly puft up with your fleſhly mind, not holding the Head?</p>
               <p>If the ſecond be ſo, then the Law and Free-grace are the ſame; if the Light God has put into all men accuſing of ſin, be the gift of Grace, the gift of heavenly Righteouſneſs by Chriſt, wherein is the end of the Law and Sin heeded: not that we are delivered from that Law in the Letter or Conſcience, that reveales ſin and wrath, and while enemies in our minds, were reconciled to God by the death of another, this is Grace; that we are ſaved in him, raiſed up into heaven in him, whilſt compaſſed about with a body of death, in our ſelves, this is a myſtery to all the Children of Reaſon, the Law and the Letter; the darkneſs that is upon it, is that which keeps the Saints in weakneſs and unſtability, the world in blindneſs and Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, and Anti-chriſt, with all his righteouſneſs, wiſdome and works after the Law, Reaſon, and Fleſh, in his power and greatneſs.</p>
               <p>If the third be ſo, then there is that in the natural man, whereby he is able to know and receave the things of the Spirit: there is a candle in all men, upon which ſome beames of the God-head do deſcend, and may be known thereby, alſo the righteouſneſs and transgreſſions of the Law; but the deep things of God, his Grace in Chriſt, ſparkling in old time now in one promiſe, now in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:48979:43"/> figured by the Law, and foretold by the Prophets; whereof the righteouſneſs of the Jewes, the Philoſophy of the Greeks, knew nothing; this cannot be diſcerned by the cleareſt Light in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural man.</p>
               <p>Thus the Myſtery of the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> and the reſtoring of all things in him, is levelled and brought down by the Divinity of theſe People, to be no other thing, than that Light of the Law and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, which all Nations have; and ſo whilſt they are condemning all other Religions, may be concluded in one common Faith and Principle, with all thoſe Religions whom they condemne, herein onely excelling them, that thoſe are Iniquity more manifeſted, theſe are Iniquity in a Myſtery: When they ſhall ceaſe to make the death of Chriſt, and the whole Myſtery of Grace in him, of none effect; I ſhall ceaſe any longer to account them ſo.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:48979:43"/>
            <head>A TABLE of the ſeveral particulars, ſpoken to in this Book.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> COncerning the Righteouſneſs of the Letter; of Angels, and of God.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> What is Idolatry: God may be known three manner of waies.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> Who hold not the Head: and how Chriſt is Head.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> Three chiefeſt Principles of this People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> examined and weighed</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5.</hi> How Faith is the Evidence of things not ſeen.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6.</hi> Concerning Faith and Sight.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7.</hi> Concerning the Spirit and Scriptures, as together making up, a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect witneſs, or rule of Faith.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8.</hi> The Light in all men, what it is, and of what uſe.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9.</hi> Two things charged upon us by this People: firſt, that we deny the Light within, and ſet it againſt Chriſt: ſecondly that we believe in a Chriſt without: theſe weighed and reſolved.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>10.</hi> What is the inward Life, and who is the retired Chriſtian.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>11.</hi> A two fold departure from the Faith in the laſt daies &amp; what they are.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>12.</hi> The Chriſt that dyed at Jeruſalem: how farre acknowledged, and how far denied by this People, to be th<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Redeemer.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>13.</hi> Whether this People build up a Righteouſneſs of the Law.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>14.</hi> Chriſt firſt and laſt Coming, what: and a Queſtion anſwered.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>15.</hi> Anti chriſts laſt Coming, what and how</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>16.</hi> The Authors Testimony, concerning the firſt and laſt Appearances of Chriſt.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>17.</hi> Light, Purity, and Power, of this People examined what it is.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>18.</hi> Oppoſition and perſecution, that is raiſed againſt this People, what to be thought of it.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>At Page 47. begins the Review of there Principles, as laid down by</hi> J. Naylor, <hi>in his Book called</hi> Love to the Loſt: <hi>under theſe ſeveral Heads.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> Concerning the fall of Man. <hi>2.</hi> Light and Life. <hi>3.</hi> Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs <hi>4.</hi> The Word. <hi>5</hi> Worſhip. <hi>6.</hi> Error and Hereſie, <hi>&amp;c. 7.</hi> Faith. <hi>8</hi> Hope. <hi>9.</hi> Judgement. <hi>10.</hi> Perfection. <hi>11.</hi> Obedience. <hi>12.</hi> Good Works <hi>13.</hi> Election, and Reprobation. <hi>14,</hi> New Birth. <hi>15.</hi> Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme of Chriſt, and that the world ſo calls. <hi>16</hi> the Lords Supper. <hi>17.</hi> Redemption. <hi>18.</hi> Juſtification. <hi>19.</hi> Sanctification, and Mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. <hi>20.</hi> The Law. <hi>21.</hi> Chriſt Jeſus. <hi>22.</hi> The Miniſters of Chriſt. <hi>23.</hi> Free-Will.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
